Good night, everyone, the speech is about to begin
各位來賓晚安,演講即將開始
Please set your phone to vibrate or silent
請將手機設定為震動或靜音
Please do not use the flash to take pictures during the speech
演講進行中,請勿使用閃光燈拍照
Thanks
謝謝
To make our lectures better
為了使我們的講座更好
Welcome everyone after the speech
歡迎各位在演講結束後
Help us scan the QR Code of the award dealer
幫我們掃描獎藝商的QR Code
Fill out our big questionnaire
給我們填大問卷
After the end at the reception desk outside the venue
結束之後在場外的接待台
There will be a small gift, thank you
會有小禮品,謝謝
Academia Sinica's 111-year Knowledge Feast
中央研究院111年知識饗宴
Dean Hu Shi's lecture begins
胡適院長講座開始
before the speech
演講開始前
Let us first ask the director-general of the China Education and Culture Foundation
我們先請中華教育文化基金會幹事長
Mr. Wang Jianya awarded us the 110th annual
王健雅先生為我們頒授110年度
Hu Shi Memorial Research Award
胡適紀念研究獎座獎牌
please the winner is also the speaker tonight
請獲獎人也是今晚的講者
Institute of Waiting History
本院靜待史研究所
Wu Renshu, a researcher, came to the stage to accept the award
烏仁樹研究員,上台領獎
and a group photo
以及合影留念
Thanks
謝謝
Then we also asked Vice President Huang to take a group photo with us
接著我們也請黃副院長一起幫我們合影留念
This is a very big book cage for a very important person of the year social sciences
這是一年一度非常重要的人物社會科學講的非常大的書籠
Congratulations to Mr. Wu, please go back to your seat first
恭喜吳老師請吳老師先回座
Let's first invite Mr. Wang Jianya, the secretary-general of the China Golden Crystal Association, to give us a speech
我們先請中華金晶會的幹事長王健雅先生為我們致辭
Vice President Huang Researcher Wu Academia Sinica
黃副院長 吳研究員 中研院
Colleagues from the highest academic unit, hello everyone
學術最高單位的同仁 大家好
Hello everyone
大家好
This Hu Shi Foundation was established in the 54th year of the Republic of China
這個胡適基金會是我們在民國54年就已經設立了
so look at him
所以你看他
It's almost 60 years now
到今年已經快要60年
However, this 60-year
但是這個60年跟中積會
The words of the China Education and Culture Foundation
中華教育文化基金會來比的話
We're almost 100 years old so in short
我們將近100年 所以很簡短的
Let me introduce the China Education and Culture Foundation
我介紹一下中華教育文化基金會
It's about following the payout
這要談到跟子賠款
It was during the Manchu Qing Dynasty that the Eight-Power Allied Forces
就是在滿清時候呢 八國聯軍
attack the party
攻黨
to this
到這個
When the city of Beijing burned down in the Yuan and Ming Dynasties
北京城 元明元燒毀的時候
So the Eight-Power Allied Forces paid compensation to Zi at that time
所以八國聯軍那個時候跟子賠款
At that time, the whole of China had about 400 million people.
那時候呢 整個中國大概是4億人
At that time, it was 10,000,000, 40,000,000
就是那個時候是萬萬 就是4萬萬
40,000,000, then each person will pay one or two yuan
4萬萬 那每人要賠一兩
So it's 40,000 taels
所以就4萬萬兩
Your history should be very clear
你們歷史應該很清楚的
After the compensation, of course there will be some military expenses.
賠了之後呢 當然還有一些軍費
The military expenditure of the Eight-Nation Allied Forces, these many blessings
八國聯軍的軍費 這些很多的福報
at that time so
那個時候 所以呢
When the government at that time was negotiating with the United States
在當時的政府跟美國協商的時候
of course
那當然
The other eight coalitions France Germany
其他八個聯軍 法國 德國
There are also blessings
也都有福報的狀況下
But the United States they admit
但是美國他們就承認
These are more parts of the blessing
這些多了 福報的部分
returned to the government at that time
就退還給那時候的政府
So about ten million
所以大概一千多萬
More than ten million dollars, that's a lot
一千多萬美金 那是很大的
a lot of money
很大的一併錢
but at that time it was a
但是那個時候是一個
Under the situation of warlord separatism
軍閥割據的狀況下
So at that time the U.S. government decided to establish
所以那時候美國政府就決定成立
Chinese Education and Culture Foundation
中華教育文化基金會
is an independent foundation
是一個獨立的基金會
the president at that time
那個時候的總統
maybe you should all know
可能你們應該都知道
It's President Cao Kun
是大總統曹昆
So our China Education and Culture Foundation
所以我們中華教育文化基金會
The mid-term meeting was established in the 24th year of the Republic of China
中期會的成立在民國24年
we still have
我們現在都還有
President Cao Kun
當初大總統曹昆
Seal established
蓋章成立
In the 24th year of the Republic of China, with Academia Sinica
民國24年 跟中研院
It's a little late for us
跟我們來講還是稍微晚了一點
Academia Sinica is the 28th year of the Republic of China
中研院是民國28年
It burned us for four years
是燒了我們四年
So we are in two years
所以呢我們在兩年
just a hundred years
就一百年
that is
也就是
Republic of China
中華民國
first foundation
第一個基金會
a hundred years in two years
在兩年就一百年
In fact, this hundred years
這一百年其實呢
We do very, very much especially in
我們做的是非常非常多 特別是在
in the early days because it was
早期的時候 因為是
The dollar is very small so we
美元是特別少 所以我們
Using these we've sponsored so many
利用這些 我們贊助了非常多
Because I was going abroad
因為當初要出國
do whatever you want to do conference
做任何你要去做conference
the equipment you want
你要的設備
all in dollars so we
全部都是美元 所以我們
During these hundred years
在這一百年當中呢
In fact, it has been
事實上呢 也一直在
Talk to all our academic units
跟我們所有的學術單位
From various institutes of Academia Sinica
從中研院各個所
And we communicated with Qingda
還有我們跟清達 交達各個
Academic units have a lot of cooperation
學術單位都有很多的合作
Then we have a lot of cooperation with Academia Sinica
那我們跟中研院很多的合作呢
right now in this
現在就是在這個
Hu Foundation
胡氏基金會
Currently 60 years
目前是60年
still we uphold the same
仍然我們秉持同樣
The original intention almost 100 years ago
快要100年前的初衷
We want to be an independent
我們希望是一個獨立的
Education and Culture Foundation
教育文化基金會
Can help all education in Taiwan
能夠幫助台灣所有教育
With the development of various cultural projects
跟文化各個項目的發展
In addition to what the government can do
除了能夠政府來做的
Of course now the government
當然現在政府
May be right for Chinese culture
可能做對中華文化的
This promotion is not so much
這種發揚並不是那麼多
then our foundation
那我們基金會
Will do more Chinese culture
會做更多中華文化
This is 100 years ago
這個就是100年前
98 years ago, our Central Accounting Association was founded
98年前我們中計會創立的
terminate us till now
終止我們到現在
have not changed
都還沒有改變
we will keep doing it
我們會一直持續做下去
Let me introduce it like this
大概這樣子介紹一下
thank you all
謝謝大家
grateful
感謝
Thank you, Director Wang
謝謝王幹事長
Now we have Vice President Huang
現在我們有請黃副院長
Host today's interview for us
為我們主持今日的採訪
today's speech
今日的演講
this
這個
Mayor Wang Gan who hit the position
衝擊位的王幹市長
The one who entered the market today's keynote speaker
那個進市所 今天主講者
Professor Wu Renshu
吳仁樹教授
And distinguished guests, it's quite cold today
還有各位貴賓今天相當的冷
So everyone listening to speeches in cold weather
那各位在冷天聽演講
is good to enjoy
是很好的享受
And Professor Wang's speech must be very exciting
而且王教授的演講一定非常的精彩
Actually he is us
其實他就是我們
In China, social economy in the Ming and Qing Dynasties
在國內 在明清社會經濟
a famous person in history
史的一個名家
In fact, many listeners also know him
其實很多聽眾也知道他
He has written quite a lot
他的著作相當的多
and it's exciting
而且很有精彩
Especially the information he used
尤其他用的資料
are very omnivorous
都是非常雜食
And delicate things like this
而細膩的東西這樣
Then his speech today
那今天他這個演講
history
要把歷史學
combined with this criminology
跟這個犯罪學結合在一起
to give an explanation
來做一個解說
this is not easy
這個很不容易
But in terms of his eloquence
不過以他的口才來講
must be very exciting
一定非常精彩
There is one today, can you wait and see?
今天有位大家可以不是拭目以待
It's Xier's court
是稀爾宮廷上
then i won't say anything
那我就都不會言了
I hope we invite Professor Wu to give us a lecture
希望我們請吳教授跟我們開講
Thanks
謝謝
Vice President Huang Director Wang Distinguished Guests
黃副院長 王幹事長 各位來賓
Hope you all have a great night tonight
今天晚上希望大家都能夠過一個非常愉快的一個夜晚
Well, I am very honored to be the speaker of Hu Shi's lecture today
那麼我今天非常榮幸能夠擔任這次胡適講座的演講者
Then I am even more honored to be able to receive from Director Wang
那我更榮幸是能夠從王幹事長的手裡
Get this very memorable lecture
拿到這次非常具有紀念意義的講座
thank you all
謝謝大家
In fact, the Central Product Association is not only a unit with a long history
中積會其實不但是一個歷史悠久的單位
At the same time, he has made great contributions to the academic and educational aspects of modern China.
同時他在近代中國的學術跟教育方面
play a very important role
都辦有非常重要的角色
I recently studied the modern Chinese agricultural students in this ruler
我在最近研究近代中國農科留學生的這個尺料裡面
You can still see that Zhongji will be inside
都還可以看到中積會在裡面
Support many Chinese international students to study abroad
支柱了許多中國的留學生到海外留學
So I see this kind of material and feel it myself
所以我看到這樣的材料自己感受到
It is a great honor to receive this award
能夠得到這個獎實在是萬分的榮幸
Everyone knows the biggest dark horse in this year's World Cup
大家都知道今年世界盃足球賽裡面最大的黑馬
It's Morocco, he made it to the semi-finals
就是摩洛哥他踢進了四強
His coach once said a word
他的教練曾經講了一句話
He said as long as you have faith
他說只要有信念
Achievement without talent
即使沒有天賦也能有所成就
I always thought I had no talent
我一直覺得我是沒有什麼天賦
no genius
沒有什麼天才的人
But I am very happy to be recognized by this award this time
但是我很高興這一次能夠受到這個獎做的認可
Then I will keep working hard
那我會持續的保持努力
create better books
創作更好的著作
To repay the attention you have given me
來回饋大家對我的重視
Then because time is limited
接下來因為時間有限
I'll go straight to our topic
我就直接進入我們的講題
Well, what I want to introduce to you today is
好 今天我要跟各位介紹的這個內容
Actually it was me recently
其實是我最近
One of my students just finished a book
跟我的一個學生剛完成了一本書
The content of this book is to discuss
這個書的內容是討論
the crime of the mid-nineteenth century
這個十九世紀中葉的犯罪
especially the problem of theft
特別是竊盜犯罪的一個問題
So I want to say that in this speech
那麼我想說這一次的演講裡面
I especially focus on history and criminology
我特別著重在歷史學跟犯罪學
how to meet
如何相遇
How the two research methods fit together
這兩個研究方法如何配合在一起
to explore the question of criminal history
來探討犯罪歷史的問題
This picture is very interesting
這個圖很有意思
It was painted in the nineteenth century
這是在十九世紀的時候所繪畫
When Westerners came to China
西方人來到中國的時候
An image painted about the outside of Chongqing City
所繪畫的關於重慶城外面的一個圖像
Next we will enter
接下來我們會進入
and record it in the content of the speech
並錄到演講的內容裡面
As far as the discussion is concerned, the eight counties in Sichuan
就討論到主要是以四川八縣
That is the place in Chongqing now as an example
也就是現在重慶的地方作為例子
Let me tell a story first
前面我先講一個故事
in the Ming and Qing Dynasties
在明清的時候
Especially in the novels of the Ming Dynasty
特別是明朝的小說裡面
There is a famous Shinto
有一個很有名的神道
also has a supernatural power
也有一個神通
Also known as Chivalry
又叫俠道
called an eyebrow
叫一支眉
Then according to the second subject of the novel, send the reporter
那麼按照小說二科派案記者
Feng Rongrong described
馮榮榮描述到
Yimei is a person in the middle of the family
一支眉是家境年間時候的人
He lives in an alley near Xuanmiao Pot in Suzhou
他住在蘇州玄妙罐附近的一個巷子
Dyed Dragon
他字號染龍
every time he succeeds in a
他每次在一個得手
after stealing
偷東西得手之後
He will draw an eyebrow flower on the wall
他就會在牆壁上畫一個眉花
draw an eyebrow
畫一支眉花
So he called it an eyebrow
所以他號稱叫一支眉
Then the illustrations in this novel
那麼這個小說裡面的插圖裡面
just drew an eyebrow
就畫了一支眉
However, this illustration
不過這個插圖畫起來
Everyone knows that in this Chinese painting
大家知道中國這個繪畫裡面的
This freehand brushwork is better than realism
這個寫意總比寫實
So everyone look carefully
所以大家仔細看起來
If you don't look carefully, you can't see it
不仔細看起來看不出來
this is a plum
這是一個梅花
I always feel that it seems to be painting a pot
總覺得它好像在鬼畫壺
Then this is freehand words
然後這個是寫意的話
Then the Godhead Will Mei described here
那麼這裡面描述的神頭意志梅
it's very powerful
它非常厲害
seems to have light work
好像有輕功
so it can jump on roofs
所以它可以登屋跳樑
it can touch the wall
它可以門牆摸壁
Coming and going like ghosts and gods coming and going like wind and rain
出入如鬼神來去如風雨
more interesting is
更有意思的是
The things it stole are Tibetan art materials
它偷到的東西是藏藝素材
What it stole was distributed to many civilians
把它偷到的東西是散給很多平民
So in this novel
所以在這個小說裡面
Admit it is the world's first thief
承它是人間第一偷
It describes the things it steals
裡面描述了它偷東西的這些
including its chivalrous behavior
包括它比如說它的俠道的行為
It sometimes steals deposits from big businessmen
它有時候會偷大商人的定金
Sometimes they steal the business of the fourth generation of Fu's family
有時候會偷四代傅家裡的經營
after stealing
偷了之後
It distributes these operations to civilians
它再把這些經營散給平民
It will also describe
另外也會描述到
it always misses when it steals
它偷東西的時候總是會失手
Sometimes it just happens to be bumped into
有時候剛好就被人碰到了
so how does it get away
所以它如何脫身
Sometimes when saplings go to this imitation house to steal silver taels
有时候苗树到这个仿制家里面偷银两的时候
Happened to be locked inside his robe cabinet.
刚好就被锁在他的衣袍的柜子里面
He just figured out how to get out
他就想办法怎么样脱身
He will pretend to be a mouse sound
他就会装着老鼠声音
Such family members think that
那样的家人以为说
There are mice in his robe
他的衣袍里面有老鼠
not open
没打开
he rushed out
他就冲出来
take this opportunity to escape
趁这个机会逃走
You can also see this sapling
另外也可以看到这个苗树
He steals clothes from this clothes store
他在这个衣服铺里面偷衣服
You can see this kind of light
就能看到这一种有足光
chase him at last
最后就追他
Then find a way when he escapes
那在他逃的时候想办法
just lost a burden
就丢了一个包袱
Everyone stopped chasing him because of the burden
大家因为标包袱就没有继续在追他
Just look at what's in the bag
就是看这个包袱里面丢什么东西
So
那么
In addition, we also saw that the story described
另外我们还看到这个故事里面描述
this one seedling
这个一只苗
He is famous because of his godhead
他因为他神头很有名
So many people want to bet with him
所以很多人都想跟他打赌
Said you have the ability to steal something from my house
说你有本事看来偷来我家的东西
try it
试试看
Including the bet he had with the commander's family
包括他跟指挥使家里的对赌
He bet against the gambler
他跟赌徒对赌
And he bet against Jiujiaweng
還有他跟九家翁對賭
In the end, even with the same strong defense
最後即使再有同強鐵壁的防守
In the end, they couldn't escape from the hands of the thief Ichimae.
最後都逃不過神偷一枝梅的手裡
So this is the magical situation that describes how he steals
所以這就描述他怎麼樣偷東西的神奇狀況
Sometimes he also teases some people
有時候他還會戲弄一些人
To tease, for example, the son who likes to show off his wealth
戲弄比如說喜歡炫富的公子哥
He put the vigilante's quilt in this boat
他把西洋義警的被子放在這個船裡面
Sometimes he also teases the priest
有時候他也會戲弄這個道士
This Taoist is unrepentant
這個道士不守輕歸
The most popular hat at the time with the swing cap
帶著擺柱帽當時最流行的帽子
go sightseeing
去游山玩水
He just secretly changed the Taoist hat
他就是偷偷摸摸把這個道士的帽子給換了
let these priests play
讓這些道士出球
Also he has an interesting story
另外他還有一個有趣的故事
It's the reflection of him helping a corrupt official to steal the censor
是他幫一個貪官去偷巡案御史的觀應
Although after unsuccessful stealing
雖然偷不成功之後
This Yizhimei still persuades this current official to say
這個義之梅還是勸這個現官說
you still put this
你還是把這個
Guan Ying returned it to Xu Anyi Shi
官映还给徐安逸史好了
Because Xu An Yishi is a smart man
因为徐安逸史是一个聪明人
is a parent
是一个亲官
if you don't pay him back
你如果不还给他
Maybe Xu Anyishi will be even more unfavorable to you in the end
说不定可能最后徐安逸史会更对你不利
But this Zixian didn't listen to him
可是这个资县不听他的话
But then the story is very interesting
可是后来的故事非常有趣
Because Xu An Yishi is not the real story of Shen You
因为徐安逸史也不是沈游的真套
He thought of a way
他就想了一个办法
After he found out his official screening had been stolen
他发现他的官映被偷了之后
He specially invited Zixian to his home for dinner
他特地请了这个资县到他家里吃饭
In the process of eating, there was a sudden fire
吃饭的这个过程中突然失火了
When there was a fire, he took the Guanying shell
失火的时候他就把官映的壳子
Empty shell
空壳子
Just pretend to be the shell of the official movie
就装官映的壳子
Give it to Zixian
交给那个资县说
you keep it for me
你帮我保管
keep it for me
帮我保管
You take it back and keep it for me
你带回去帮我保管
I'm going to fight the fire
我要去救火了
This Zixian returned home with an empty Guanying shell
这个资县拿着空的官映壳子回到家里面
just want to say no
就想说不对
i stole his official movie
我偷了他的官映
Now he's giving me the empty shell
现在他把空壳子包给我
If I don't put the official screening back
我如果不把官映放回去的话
He took it and saw the empty shell
他拿了看到空壳子
He said I stole it
他说是我偷的
what to do with this hand
这手怎么办
He had no choice but to put the official movie back obediently.
他只好乖乖的把官映放回去
that empty box
那個空盒子
Xu Anyi got this
徐安逸是拿到了這個
Vis empty box see
Vis空盒子看到
about being in
關於在裡面
Of course there is plenty of luggage
當然行李有數
good guy
好家伙
It's because your branch line is expensive.
就是你這個支線搞得貴
Sure enough, after Xu Anyi found out about this situation,
果然徐安逸是知道了這個情況之後
think of a way right away
馬上就想的辦法
turn off this soup
把這個湯關給治了
This of course this is an interesting one about
這個當然這個是一個有趣的關於
this heroic story
這個俠道的故事
But in this story
可是這個故事裡面
we clearly know
我們很明顯知道
A lot of this story is pieced together
這故事裡面很多是拼湊而來的
how do you put it together
怎麼說拼湊而來
The most obvious is
最明顯的就是
He is capable of stealing a house
他都有能力去偷關家
The one who stole the silver from this generation's father's house
就偷這個世代父家裡的銀子的
Then why is he still stealing clothes?
那他幹嘛還去偷衣服呢
Stealing clothes from these clothes shops?
偷這些衣服鋪的衣服呢
That is to say
也就是說
which example
哪個比方
If there is a thief today
如果今天有個賊
Already capable of stealing bank vaults
都已經有能力去偷銀行的金庫了
But why is he going to UNICORO to steal clothes?
但幹嘛他還去UNICORO偷衣服呢
so in this story
所以這個故事裡面
Of course, a lot of them are pieced together.
當然是很多是拼湊而來的
but is there such a person
但是有沒有這個人呢
do you have an eyebrow
有沒有一支眉呢
Until now
到現在為止
Many scholars have not verified
很多學者沒有考證
But I just found out
但是我剛好考證了出來
Yizhimei does have this person
義之梅的確有這個人
And this person is in Yongzhou Prefecture, Hunan Province
而且這個人是在湖南的永州府
he is an avenue
他是個大道
Then he was cured by an official
然後當時被一個官員給治了
So left this record at that time
所以當時留下了這個記錄
So this Yizhimei is indeed someone
所以這個義之梅確實是有些人
but he is not a thief
但是他不是一個偷
he is not a thief
他不是一個小偷
he is an avenue
他是個大道
But let's come back and talk about this issue
可是回過來我們再來講這個問題
the study of criminal history
就是歷史學關於犯罪史的研究
In fact, the aspect of our past historical research
其實我們過去歷史學研究的面向
getting bigger and bigger
越來越擴重越來越廣
But the study of criminal history itself
可是對於犯罪歷史本身的研究
but for a long time
卻長期以來
arguably underappreciated or ignored
可以說沒有受到重視或忽略
Of course there are several reasons
當然有幾種原因
Because most of the historiography
因為大部分歷史學
To focus more on big events
要比較聚焦於大事件的一些
The outcome of major events in history
歷史上的大事件的結果
such as war, revolution
比如說戰爭、革命
For example, the war of the Taiping Heavenly Kingdom
比如說太平天國的戰爭
Xinhai Revolution
辛亥革命
and the daytime rebellion
還有白天教的叛亂
Even local food looting riots
甚至地方上的搶糧暴動
these are historians past
這些是歷史學家過去
very careful things
非常會注意的事情
But about some everyday crimes
可是關於一些日常性的犯罪
something like a thief
像小偷 小道這個東西
In fact, historians have
其實歷史學家過去
I don't pay much attention to this research
就不太注意這個研究
Of course not too much research
當然不太注意研究
There is another reason
也有一個另外一層原因
Issues involving so-called historical materials
涉及到所謂史料的問題
The so-called cleverness is hard to come by without rice
所謂巧負難為無米之吹
as a historical research
作為一個歷史研究
you still have to have history
你還是必須要有史料
then it's a pity
那麼很可惜的是
History about this theft
關於這個偷竊的史料
like we mentioned
就像我們剛才提到
There are some descriptions in the novel notebook novel
小說 筆記小說裡面有一些描述
Then there are some descriptions in the koan novel
那麼公案小說裡面也有一些描述
Interpretation is some
判讀就是當時一些
In these interpretations left by generations of husbands
世代夫留下來的這些判讀裡面
There are also some descriptions
也有一些描述
But these are sporadic and not enough
但是這些都是零星而不夠整體
We can't see a whole
我們沒辦法看到一個整體的
Holistic aspect of stealing
偷竊的整體的面向
Well, again, the development of history in the past 20 years
好 再次20年來歷史學的發展
Especially the history of Ming and Qing Dynasties
特別是明清史的部分
Especially during the history of the Qing Dynasty
特別是清代歷史的時候
China has archives of many prefectures, counties and local counties
中國有許多州縣地方縣的檔案
was excavated
被發掘出來
still very complete
還非常的完整
in these judicial files
這些司法檔案裡面
preserve quite a few of these cases of theft.
就保留了相當多關於偷竊的這些案子
so that we historians can study
讓我們歷史學家可以好好的研究
Of course when researching
當然在研究的時候
We also hope that there will be a breakthrough in the method
我們也希望在方法上要有突破
So in the study of history in the past
所以在過去研究歷史裡面
In fact, about the legal system
其實關於法律制度
Social Phenomena Reflected by Law
關於法律反映的社會現象
Such studies are more common in the past
這樣的研究是過去比較常看到的
But now if we want to focus on
但是我們現在如果想要把重心
when moving to criminal history
轉移到犯罪的歷史的時候
we need to update the method
我們就需要更新的方法
which i think
其中我覺得
We can combine the so-called
我們可以結合的所謂的
Criminology and History
犯罪學跟歷史學
That's what I'm talking about today
這也就是我今天講說
Historical criminology is a new direction to do research
歷史犯罪學是做一個研究的新方向
then the history of the past
那麼歷史學過去
we just mentioned
我們剛才提到了
Pay attention to historical events
重視歷史大事件
Also pay attention to changes in some social structures
也重視一些社會結構的變化
legal system
也重視法律制度
also pay attention to
也重視
litigation process
訴訟過程
aka police
也就是警察治安
such a system
這樣的制度
this is us historians past
這是我們歷史學家過去
more often noticed
在比較常注意的
criminology
可是犯罪學
its angle
它的角度
Let's have some more interesting history
讓我們歷史學有一些更有趣的
Aspects of development neglected
發展而忽略的面向
Except social change is the past
除了社會變遷是過去
everyone has been
大家一直
whether history or criminology
不論是歷史學或犯罪學
other than the important issues that everyone will pay attention to
都會注意的重要的議題之外
then the cause of the crime
那麼犯罪所形成的原因
Also discussed in criminal psychology
還有犯罪心理學裡面所討論的
perpetrator's motive
犯罪者的動機
criminal psychology
犯罪者的心理
in criminology
還有犯罪學裡面
Discuss how to prevent crime
討論如何防治犯罪
how to avoid crime
如何能夠避免犯罪
And these angles and this orientation
而這幾個角度和這個面向
but our history of the past
卻是我們過去歷史學
less noticeable
比較少注意到的
so we can try
所以我們可以嘗試的
Using research methods from these two disciplines
用把這兩個學門的研究方法
combine together
結合在一起
let's have some new discussions
來做一些新的討論
what about here
那麼這裡呢
I will commit crimes by cutting
我就用切道犯罪
discuss as an example
作為例子來討論
So what's the point of cutting to crime?
那麼切到犯罪有什麼重要呢
How to do research
那要怎麼樣去研究呢
First of all, we all feel that
首先呢我們都會覺得說
there are all kinds of crime
犯罪有各式各樣
So what does it matter when it comes to crime?
那麼切到犯罪到底它有什麼重要呢
Next, I will use the eight-line file
接下來我就是用八線檔案
As you can see in the example of the eight-line file
大家看到八線檔案的這個例子裡面
This is all the eight line files
這是八線檔案所有的這個
From Qianlong tide to Xuantong tide
從乾隆潮一直到宣統潮
according to its category
按照它的類別呢
The statistics of these numbers
所做的這些數量的統計
Then we can see from here
那麼我們從這裡可以看到
cut to this class
切到這個類
cut to this class in the middle
切到這個類在中間
It is the largest number of almost every trendy bag
它幾乎是每一個潮袋都是數量最多的
The biggest amount
數量最多
Especially as I am now discussing the middle of the 19th century
尤其我現在討論到19世紀中
also when homosexuality
也同志潮的時候
You see it has more than 3,000 pieces
大家看它有3000多件
That comrade is only ten years old
那同志也不過十幾年
you average
你平均算起來
About 200 cases a year
大概一年就大概有200多個案件
I feel very sympathetic at this time
這時候我就非常同情
gay tide at that time
同志潮那個時候
Why is he restricting the limit?
他限制支限 為什麼
Every year he light theft
他每一年光竊盜案
He will try more than 200 cases
他就要審理兩百多件
it's still theft
這還是竊盜案
He has other cases to be sentenced
還有其他案件他還要判
So the former constituency
所以以前的憲官
Especially in the mid-19th century of the Qing Dynasty
特別是到了清朝中葉十九世紀
Constitutional Officer of the Qing Dynasty
清朝的憲官
really busy
真是忙啊
For those constitutional officials at that time
我們對於當時這些憲官
120,000 sympathies from the rainstorm
暴雨十二萬分的同情
It can also be seen from here
從這裡也可以看到
High number of thefts
竊盜案數量之多
is one thing we should not ignore
是我們不應該忽略一件事情
Because there are too many of them
因為他實在數量太多了
Here I also mentioned the eight-line file
這裡我也提到八線檔案
The eighth line is now Chongqing
八線就是現在的重慶
Because of the emergence of eight-line files and
因為有八線檔案的出現和
so that we can study well
讓我們可以好好地研究
these theft cases
這些竊盜案件
good
好
So let's introduce
那麼我們先介紹一下
If the law of the Qing Dynasty
如果在清朝的法律
How to judge the so-called
如何去判所謂的
regulate this law
規範這個法律
How to regulate the problem of theft
如何規範竊盜的問題
we know qing dynasty
我們知道大清
General Laws of the Qing Dynasty
清朝大致上的法律
into two categories
分成兩類
one is green one is green
一個是綠一個是綠
is a female Dharma
是一個母法 利是指法
In this law, in the crime of the sword
在這個律裡面 對於確刀犯罪裡面
A few more important points
又強調幾個重點
First of all, it does not emphasize hand bugs
首先它非強調手蟲
That is, who is leading and who is following
也就是誰是帶頭的 誰是跟隨的
So the big brother who takes the lead is punished more severely.
所以帶頭大哥他處罰的是比較重的
The little brother I follow is a little lighter
跟的小弟是稍微輕的
Second, he will pay attention to the problem of offenders and repeat offenders
第二個他會注意出犯跟累犯的問題
That is to say, your autumn cut
也就是說你這個秋切
If you committed a crime
這個犯案的時候 你如果是出犯
I will give you a lighter punishment
我給你比較輕的來處罰
But when you get to the third offense
但是到你犯到第三犯的時候
That's behind the toes
那就是腳尖後了
It's the highest law
就是一個最高的法律了
But it looks like everyone has two chances
不過這樣子看起來好像大家有兩次機會
that you can do it again
就是你可以再犯一次
The third important principle is called Ji Zhang Lun Punishment
第三個重要的它的原則叫濟章論刑
That is to say, for the Qing Dynasty, the theft
也就是說清朝對於偷竊
Its sentence is based on the value of the items you stole
它的判刑是根據你偷竊章物的價值高低
The higher the value, the higher your judgment
價值越高 你判得行越高
Walk
走
For example, like here, below one or two, it is judged as 60
比如說像這裡,一兩以下它是判仗60
This spanking only costs 60
這打屁股只要60
But if you are 42 to 50 taels
但是你如果是42到50兩的話
In addition to playing version 68, you
你除了要打68版之外
You have another year in prison
你還要徒刑一年
going to prison for one year
要去做徒刑一年
a year in prison
做一年的牢役
If you are 82 to 90 taels
如果你是82到90兩的話
You don't need to fight 100
你不大要仗100
you will be in prison for three years
你要徒三年
If it is 92 to 100 taels
如果是92到100兩的話
you still have to stay
你還要留
Except battle 100
除了仗100以外
you want to be popular
你要流行
to distribute frontier
要發配邊疆
To reserve two thousand miles
要留配兩千里
So wait until 120 taels or more
所以等到120兩以上
will pay the back
就要繳肩後
This sentence is based on the value of the amount you steal
這種按照你的偷竊數量的價值來判刑
I think the sentencing decider is very interesting
我都覺得判刑決定者非常有趣
If our current law
如果我們現在的法律裡面
If such a sentence is used for a fraud case
對於詐騙案用這樣的判刑的話
most scammers
大部分的詐騙人
probably to death
大概都要關到死
good
好
Then in addition to the mother law
那麼除了母法以外
law enforcement
執法這一方面
There are also some changes
也有一些變化
And the new crime situations they're adapting to
而且他們適應的新的犯罪情況
Especially the tired meal is too much
特別是那個累飯實在太多了
So everyone wants to define these tired meals
所以大家就想要如何定義這些累飯
So give it a name called chicken foot slippery
所以給它一個名詞叫雞腓滑賊
And find a way to prevent these tired meals from happening
而且要想辦法阻止這些累飯的發生
So at that time, a kind of criminal law was invented in many places
所以當時有很多地方上就發明一種刑法
It's called Iron Cover Iron Lock Strap
叫做鐵蓋 鐵桿鎖帶
that is to say with a hardcore
就是說用個鐵桿
Then there must be an iron strap to lock it to the foot
然後要有一個鐵帶把它鎖在腳
or locked in the neck
或鎖在脖子裡面
Let it be carried like this
讓它平常就得這樣子帶著
avoid it later
避免它以後再犯刑
do the theft again
再犯這個偷竊案
But later we'll just look at an image and find out
不過等會我們就看一個圖像而發現
even though it already has this thing
即使它已經帶了這個東西
still commit crimes
還是會犯罪
In addition, it also mentioned that there is a principle
另外它也講到有一個原則
Just to increase the punishment
就是要加重量刑
That is, there was violence during the theft.
就是在偷竊的過程中有暴力行為
The crime of murder with a gray knife is aggravated
有灰刀殺人的這種情況加重刑責
Other crimes in certain places with special status
另外某些特殊身份場所的犯罪
will also increase the penalty
也會加重刑責
Those special status fields
那這些特殊身份場
Status and place are usually related to the official or royal family
身份跟場所通常都涉及到官家或皇室
So if you committed a crime in a royal or official place
所以你如果是在皇室或官家的場所裡面犯罪的話
you will pretend to be criminal
你會假裝刑責
There is another very interesting phenomenon
另外還有一個很有趣的現象
But China's special situation
可是中國特別有的情況
This is still the case in the Republic of China
一直到現在中華民國還是有這個情況
crimes against relatives
就是跟親屬關係犯罪
It is very special except criminal law
它除了刑法是很特別
because of family crimes
因為親屬犯罪裡面
it is based on your kinship to convict
它是根據你的親屬關係去定罪
So when you especially immediate family members
所以你特別是直系親屬的時候
Its crimes, its convictions are very light
它的犯罪、它的定了罪是非常輕
not even guilty
甚至等於沒有罪
Until now, in the Constitution of the Republic of China
一直到現在中華民國的憲法裡面
sin of theft
偷竊的罪裡面
If the son steals the books from the father's immediate family members
如果是兒子偷老爸直系親屬的偷本
It's not a crime
其實是不構成犯罪的
This is a very interesting penal code
這是一個非常有趣的刑法
until now
一直到現在
In addition, of course, the type of dirt is also related to criminal responsibility.
另外當然跟髒物的種類也跟刑責有關
That is, you stole the dirt
也就是你偷了髒物裡面
If it is public dirt
如果是公家的髒物
It's official dirt
是官家的髒物
The penalty is even heavier
那刑責就更重
In addition, if you are involved in a crime
另外你如果是一起犯罪裡面
In addition to the so-called master-slave
除了所謂主從之外
If you are a criminal harboring
你如果是窩藏的犯罪
Or you are accepting his stamp
或者說你是收他的章物的
there are penalties
這也有刑罰
In addition, the official duties must also be mature.
那另外這個官義施職也要成熟
If you are an official or a patch
如果你這個官或者是補塊
none of you
你都沒有
Didn't catch the thief
都沒有去抓小偷的話
Even if he was not caught, there is a law to accept responsibility.
都沒抓到他也是有接責法
Then obviously we can see the laws of the Qing Dynasty
那顯然我們可以看到清朝的法律
He's not actually a piece of iron
他其實不是鐵板與塊的
He will actually adapt to the changes in the whole society
他其實是會適應整個社會變遷
Also some new updates
也有些新的更新
And these laws and forces are constantly changing
而且這些律跟力都不斷的在更改之中
so these criminals
所以這些犯罪的
In the law of these congratulatory crimes
這些賀主犯罪的法律裡面
In fact, the rules are quite detailed
其實定則是相當細的
Then use this method to congratulate the Lord for committing a crime
再用這個方法來賀主犯罪
Let's see next
接下來我們來看
If a crime has occurred
如果發生了犯罪的案件之後
how does he report the crime
他怎麼樣去報案
how to deal with these
怎麼樣去處理這些
How does the government handle these processes
官府怎麼樣處理這些流程
when the crime first occurred
首先發生犯罪的時候
ordinary people
一般的老百姓
Maybe he didn't report to the police right away first.
可能他不是先馬上去報官
He first went to the neighborhood near his house
他先去找他家附近的
so-called group training
所謂的團練
or Baojiachang
或者是保甲長
He first talked with Tuan Lian and Bao Jia Chang
他先跟團練跟保甲長講
He said so-and-so's house stole something from him
他說某某人家偷了他什麼什麼的東西
It's time for group training
這時候團練呢
With this Baojia chief, the two trillion
跟這個保甲長就會把這個兩兆
to this place for mediation
到這個地方上做調解
Much like our mediation committee now
就很像我們現在調解委員會
Let's mediate first
先做調解一下
If mediation fails
如果調解不成
In the end they will sue
最後呢他們才會告官
Then after suing the officer
那麼告官之後
will present his son
會呈上他的壯子
or pie
或餅狀
Say so and so or when in Zhuangzi
在壯子裡面說某某人或什麼時候
my house was stolen
我家裡被偷了
or when so and so stole from me
或某某人什麼時候偷了我
what did you steal
偷了什麼東西呢
I will list the so-called Shi Dan
我會列舉的就是所謂施丹
In Shidan, it will be listed as
在施丹裡面會列舉說
something was stolen from my house
我家裡什麼什麼東西被偷
list them one by one
一項一項的列出來
even put his this
甚至會把他的這個
The price of this item will also be listed
這個物品的價格也會列出來
then this time
那麼這個時候
After the branch accepts the report
支線接受了這個報案之後
Then he started investigating
之後他就開始調查
First of all, he will shoot calligraphy
首先他會拍書意
to that scene
到那個現場
do something called this
做一些所謂的這個
CSI crime scene to do some investigation
CSI犯罪現場做一些調查
An investigative report written after the crime scene investigation
犯罪現場調查之後會寫的一個調查報告
call bulletin
叫刊單
This is the bulletin left at that time
這就是當時留下來的刊單
This bulletin is written very carefully
這刊單裡面寫得非常仔細
They said this man, Yu Fuxing, had his home burglarized
他們說這個人余復興他家裡被竊
where does he live
他住在什麼地方
He lives at the Jiaochangkou of the official temple
他住在官廟的教場口
His house is a pavement
他的這個房子是一個鋪面
is a shop
是一個商店
The distance between pavements is two
鋪面的間隔是兩近的
There is a cabinet room in front
前面有櫃房
in front of the counter
前面是櫃台
There is a tall building in the back
後面有安了一個高樓
Then there is a small door on the left side of the wall with a
然後左邊的牆壁側有個小門有一道
what's next near the middle
接下來接近中間的有什麼東西
He also said that there was a piece of bamboo on his wall
他還講說他的這個夾壁有一片竹片
but he is renovating
但是他正在整修
So when he is on the street next to the outside
所以他跟外面鄰街的時候
The walls of the refurbished bamboo pieces have no cement on the lake
整修的竹片的牆壁沒有湖上水泥
So he said there were thieves at that time
所以他說那個時候就有賊
the empty house next door to him
他隔壁的空房子
ran from his empty house to his house
從他的空房子跑到他家裡來
and then stole something
然後就偷了什麼什麼什麼東西
He said the last book meaning, I found out from the investigation
最後這個書意他有說 我調查的結果發現
This crossing is indeed a crossing.
這個道口啊 量起來的確有道口
How much does it measure? 20 1 inches wide and 1 15 inches wide
量起來有高多少 20 1吋 有寬1 15吋
Such this wall was found with damaged heart muscle
這樣的這個牆壁被找開來 有毀損的心肌
So he will do a survey like this
所以他會做一個這樣的刊單調查出來
What about sometimes, the Shuyi Association said in a survey
那有時候呢 這個書意會調查說
They found the scene, with the informant
他們發現這個現場啊 跟這個報案者
Reporter's description must not match
報案者的描述必不符合
Then the branch will start to suspect that this may be a case of false reporting.
那麼支線就會開始懷疑 這個可能是謊報的案子
there will be such a judgment
會有這樣的判斷
Well, if it is determined that he is indeed a case,
那麼如果確定了 他的確是一個案件的話
Calligraphy will start, and this branch line will send an official document to guess the ticket
書意就開始 這個支線就下一道公文給猜票
Ask that man to start to mend, and then start to catch the bandit according to the plan
叫那個補意開始去補 就開始按圖所計去抓這個盜匪
catch the thief
抓這個小偷
Then if this supplement catches the thief
那麼如果這個補意抓到了小偷之後
he'll subpoena the victim
他就會傳喚這個受害者
and general
還有一般的
A dry line of witnesses begins the interrogation
一乾的證人開始審訊
Then the official document of these summons is called Peteran
那麼這些傳喚的這個公文叫做彼丹
Then after the arraignment they said
那麼傳訊之後他們講
Each will have their own job status and confession
會各有自己的工狀有口供說
how was that day
那天怎麼樣怎麼樣
why am i
我是什麼什麼原因
These final confessions are left behind and are called work certificates.
最後這些口供留下來叫做工狀
In the end, of course, the case was closed.
最後當然這個案子結了
we used to watch this tv
我們以前看這個電視機
there will be pressure
都會有畫壓
The pressure of the painting is a knot
畫的壓就是一個結狀
The whole process looks like this
整個流程是這個樣子
But in fact we will find
但是事實上我們會發現
Most of the cases are basically unsolved
大部分的案件基本上都沒辦法結案
because most of the theft cases
因為大部分的偷竊案件
Very low detection rate
破案率非常低
so let's see
所以我們來看
now probably theft
現在大概偷竊案
For example, in Taipei now
以現在比如說在台北的
In terms of the police capacity of Taipei City
以台北市的警察能力來講
Theft cases probably have a detection rate of 80 or 90%.
偷竊案大概破案率都有80、90%
80, 90% or more
80、90%以上
Plus this monitor that we have installed for the last time
再加上我們現在倒數都裝的這個監視器
So in fact, the detection rate of this kind of theft is quite high.
所以其實這種偷竊的破案率是頗高的
But in traditional things, it's actually not too high
但是在傳統的事情其實就不太高
There was a missionary
當時有一位傳教士
called Morrison
叫Morrison
he had been to 1894
他曾經到過1894年
have been to chongqing
曾經到過重慶
But he spoke highly of the public security in Chongqing.
可是他對重慶的這個治安評價很高
He said that the law and order in Chongqing is very good.
他說這個重慶產內的治安非常好
very good
非常好
But everyone should pay attention
但是大家要注意
This description is actually a comparison
這種描述其實都是比較而來的
are compared
都是比較而來
In other words, when these Westerners came to China
也就是說這些西方人來到中國的時候
He said good is not absolutely good
他說好並不是絕對的好
is relatively good
是相對的好
It was also compared to when he was in some cities in Europe
也是相對他當時在歐洲某些城市
In China, Chongqing is a city with good law and order
中國在重慶這個城市是治安好
what is it actually like
那實際上是怎麼樣呢
uncertain
不一定
Let's follow my statistics
我們來按照我做的統計
We see cases in the city
我們看到在都市裡面的案件
What happened in Chongqing at that time
有當時在重慶發生的
There are more than 1,000 cases in the city
都市裡面的案件有1000多件
Then
然後
In the end, only 204 suspects were obtained
最後獲得嫌犯只有204件
So he only has a 19% cracking rate.
所以他破案率只有19%
country?
鄉村呢
His case count is more than 1900
他的案件數有1900多件
Getting a case to crack is 6
獲得案件以破獲是6
The true detection rate is 33%.
那真正破案率有33%
In the countryside is better than in the city
在鄉村還比在都市裡面
higher detection rate
破案率高一點
but even so
但是即使如此
Its average detection rate is only 28%.
它的平均破案率也不過28%
So you can say this
所以你能說當時的這個
Is the detection rate high?
破案率高嗎
of course not
當然不可能
so it's only relatively good
所以它只是相對的好
relatively good
相對好
there is another interesting thing
那另外還有一個有趣的事情
is actually
就是其實
After many of these suspects were caught,
很多這些嫌犯被抓了之後
put in jail
放在監獄
Most closed for less than a month
大部分關不到一個月
probably hang up
就大概就掛了
will die in prison
就會死在監獄裡面
Then you know that in this prison at that time
那你就知道在當時這個監獄裡面
In fact, the conditions are very bad
其實條件是非常不好的
So a lot of these suspects are in jail
所以很多這些嫌犯在監獄裡面
It's hard to survive more than a month
都很難熬過一個月以上
Hard to survive more than a month
很難熬過一個月以上
ok, let's see
好 接下來我們來看
Context affecting crime rates
影響犯罪率的背景
I use this picture to estimate
這個圖我是來估計
During the gay boom
在同志潮這段時間的
This cuts to the number of crimes
這個切到犯罪的數量
everyone see
大家看到
From the first year of being gay to the 13th year of being gay
從同志元年到同志13年
its this cut to case number
它的這個切到案件數量
Very interesting
很有意思的
There is an interesting phenomenon in this figure
這個圖裡面呈現一個有趣現象
That is to say
也就是說
Comrades from the first year to the sixth year
同志元年到六年
His theft cases are very high
他的偷竊案件是非常高的
But after seven years of gay
但是到了同志七年之後
slowly lowered
就慢慢降低了
lowered a lot
就降低了很多
then this time
那麼這一段時間
why during this time
這段時間為什麼會
why is his case high
他的案件為什麼會高
In fact, if we take a closer look
其實如果我們再仔細看
In the historical background of the time
當時的歷史大背景裡面
You will find at least a few reasons
你會發現至少有幾個原因
is responsible for the growth of this cutter case
是造成這個切刀案件增長的原因
and also directly reflected in the
而且還會直接反映在當時的
Inside the case of the cutter case
切刀案件的那個案件裡面
For example, the Taiping Heavenly Kingdom
比如說太平天國
Everyone knows the Taiping Heavenly Kingdom
大家知道這個太平天國
In fact, the first year of comrades is already the end of the strong humiliation
其實到同志元年已經是強辱之末
But there was their
可是當時有個他們的
To Wing King Ten Open
要翼王十大開
He entered Chongqing in the first year of comrades
他在同志元年的時候進入到重慶
into Sichuan Province
進入到四川省
harassed the harassed
騷擾了這個騷擾
He entered Sichuan Province from here
他從這邊進入到四川省
Then he went to Guizhou
然後他又到了貴州
Then in the second year of comrades
然後在同志二年的時候
He's here again from
他又到了這個從
Arrived in Sichuan again
又到了四川
Finally annihilated in this place
最後在這個地方被殲滅了
But in the process of his arrival in Sichuan
可是他到了四川的過程之中
No direct access to Chongqing
沒有直接進入到重慶
But I have entered the surrounding areas of Chongqing
但是入過了重慶的周圍
That is, around Baxin
也就是八信的周圍
So at that time many cases
所以在當時那個很多案件
cut into the case
切當案件裡面
It is said that many victims are group trainers
講很多受害者是團練
Why did team training suffer?
為什麼團練受害
Because of the group practice, he has to go to many arts outlets
因為團練他要去很多藝口
to guard against these Taipings
去防這些太平軍
But there is no one in his family
可是他家裡就沒有人了
So the house becomes
所以家裡就變成了
Good example of a break-in
闖空門的好例子
So a lot of team practice to defend Yikou
所以很多團練去防守藝口
When he came back, he found that his house had been burglarized.
回來之後發現他家被偷了
a lot of it is because
很多都是因為
many of these victims
很多這些受害者
It's because of the Taiping Heavenly Kingdom
是因為太平天國的原因
indirect damage
間接造成的受害
What does the second reason have to do with it?
第二個原因跟什麼有關呢
Happened with comrades for two years
跟同志二年發生的
The lesson plans in Chongqing are related
重慶的教案有關係
The Comrade Two Years Happened in Chongqing
同志二年是重慶發生的
Anti-Catholic Teaching Plan
反天主教的教案
At that time, many groups of mobs
當時很多一批暴民
Just run to Catholics
就跑去天主教的教徒的
These residential areas go down
這些住宅地區去倒
to rob, to burn
去搶 去燒殺
There are also many people taking advantage of this time
也有很多人趁這個時候
to name the thing that was stolen from that residence
去叫名那個住所裡面偷竊的東西
After those people who stole were slowly caught
那偷竊這些人慢慢被抓了之後
they tell their reasons
他們就講出他們的理由
It was when I was gay for two years
就是同志二年的時候
I'm taking advantage of the chaos
我是趁亂
Seeing this, I just touched something and came back
看到這樣我就是摸了一些東西回來
So in fact this turmoil
所以其實這種動亂
Endemic unrest can also affect cheetao cases
地方性動亂也會影響到切道案件
Then the third reason is related to the price
那麼第三個原因跟物價有關
related to this economic change
跟這個經濟變遷有關
Because in the three years of many comrades
因為在很多同志三年的
a lot of these thieves got caught
很多這些被抓到的小偷
His statement said
他的口供裡面都說
Why did I steal that year
我那一年為什麼要去偷竊
Because he said that the price of rice was too expensive that year
因為他說那一年米價太貴
It's too high for me to live
一下太高了我的難以生活
so now i have to steal
所以我現在只好去偷竊
Is it like this let's see
是不是這樣子我們來看一下
Actually this is what I got from
其實這是我從
inside the file
檔案裡面
a price list
所做的一個物價表
We will find that in 1864 when
我們會發現在1864年的時候
The price of rice has suddenly risen
這個米價突然上升了
and increased several times
而且上升了好幾倍
The highest rice price is from 2 taels
最高的米價從2兩
Rise to 3.5 Taels
上升到3.5兩
It's going to be high
接下來就一直在高點
The same is true for the lowest rice price
最低的米價也是這個樣子
So in the third year of Tongzhi
所以在同治三年的時候
Because of the sudden rise in the price of rice
因為米價突然的高漲
At that time, there were many people because of the high price of rice
在當時有很多人就是因為米價高
he ended up having trouble living
他最後難以生活
end up stealing
最後去偷竊東西
The fourth reason is a long-term factor
第四個原因是一個長期的因素
Long-term factors have a lot to do with urbanization
長期因素跟都市化有很大的關係
Why? This is a statistic I made
為什麼?這是我做的一個統計
The urban population of this eighth-tier region
這個八線地區的城市人口
This is his total population
這是他的總人口數
Let's figure out the percentage of urbanization in his city
我們來算算出他的城市都市化的比例
As you can see in 1824
大家看到在1824年的時候
The proportion of urbanization is 14%
都市化比例是14%
This is probably the traditional Chinese period
這大概是中國傳統時期
average proportion of urbanization in general
一般的都市化的平均比例
about ten percent
大概是百分之十幾
But by the 1860s
但是到1860年代
That's when it's good to have the same government
也就是同政才好的時候
His urbanization ratio suddenly rose to 32%
他的都市化比例突然上升到32%
this city
這個城市
Chongqing city developed in private land
重慶城在私有之地出
He changed from a population of tens of thousands
他一下從幾萬人口
Population from 65,000 to 200,000
6.5萬人口暴增到20萬人口
The degree of urbanization suddenly increased at this time
都市化程度突然在這時候暴增起來
Then continue to grow slowly and continuously
然後一直延續慢慢的 延續的成長
So at this time we will find
所以在這個時候我們就會發現
If we compare the 18th century to the mid-19th century
如果我們比較18世紀跟19世紀中葉的時候
You can find an interesting phenomenon
你們就可以發現一個有趣現象
In the second half of the 18th century during the Qianlong Dynasty
在乾隆朝18世紀下半葉的時候
His theft case is actually not too many
他的這個偷竊案件其實不太多
Only more than 300 pieces
只有300多件
Then the proportion that happens in the city is 19%
然後發生在城市的比例是19%
Occurred in rural areas is 81%
發生在鄉村是81%
So most of the cases are in rural areas
所以大部分都是在鄉村的案件
But in Tong Zhichao's 3,000-plus theft cases,
可是到了童志朝數量暴增的3000多件的竊案中
The proportion of cities takes place in cities as high as 33%
城市的比例發生在城市的比例高達33%
The proportion that occurred in rural areas has dropped to 59%
發生在鄉村的比例已經降到59%
So this whole trend is related to urbanization
所以這個整個趨勢都跟都市化有關
So urbanization will actually affect the growth of the crime rate
所以都市化其實會影響到犯罪比例的增長
Especially in the urban crime growth
特別在都市犯罪增長
this is a situation
這是一個情況
Okay, the next question is fun.
好 下面一個問題 好玩了
What kind of person is likely to become a thief
什麼樣的人容易會成為竊賊
What kind of person is prone to crime
什麼樣的人會有犯罪的傾向
Generally we think that
一般我們都會認為說
Especially the so-called fringe people who don't do their jobs properly
特別是那種所謂的不務正業的邊緣份子
a so-called dangerous class
是一種所謂的危險階級
Including things like implement, beggar
包括了像貫徹啊 乞丐啊
No business, or some thieves
不務正業啊 或一些賊匪啊
Hooligans, liars
地皮流氓啊 騙子啊
OK, but I'm based on myself from this cutter case
好 可是我根據我自己從這個切刀案件
Tong Zhichao's case made some statistics
童志潮的案件做了一些統計
The number of these people is certainly not small.
這些人的數量 當然也不算少
But the real, the real majority is this group of people
但是真正 真正最多數的是這批人
Xia Li is alive
叫夏立活生的
they are working class
他們是勞動階層
But the fluid working class
但是不固定的勞動階層
He is not the same as the sailor on the ship and the porter
他跟這個船運的水手跟搬運的腳夫是不一樣
Because sailors and porters are regular occupations
因為水手跟腳夫他們是固定職業的
they have trade unions
他們有同業工會
they have fixed groups
他們有固定的團體
But this Xia Li is not a fixed industry group
但是這個夏立活生的是沒有固定的這個同業團體
So this group of people is the group of people who are most prone to stealing.
所以這批人反而是最容易傾向於偷竊的一批人
steal a bunch of people
偷竊一批人
but except for these people
但是除了這些人
Except in more than 200 months
除了在200多月
More than 200 Summer Law live outside
200多個夏律活生之外
everyone can see
大家可以看到
There are so many businessmen
工商業者有那麼多人
There are more than 100 people employed in the service industry
受雇服務業的也有一百多人
civil servant or gene
公務人員或基因
He himself may be a thief
他本身也有可能是偷竊者
We have some social relations
大家還有些社會關係
so this lets us
所以這就讓我們
thought of another interesting thing
想到另外一件有趣的事情
would be a thief
就是會成為偷竊者
Not necessarily all directly related to poverty
不一定都跟貧窮直接有關
Because some people are professional
因為有一些人是有職業
also have income
也有收入
but they steal
但是他們會偷竊
so what's the reason
那麼這是什麼原因
Next we discuss
接下來我們就討論到
question of motive
犯罪動機的問題
The question of motive for theft
竊盜犯罪動機的問題
Do the poor always steal?
窮人一定會偷竊嗎
that's right
是沒錯
they may be inclined to steal
他們可能會傾向偷竊
but not all
但並不是所有的
poor people steal
窮人都會偷竊
And why the poor steal
而且窮人之所以偷竊
there are many promotions
還有很多促進
the reason it becomes a thief
它變成竊盜犯的原因
and motivation
和動機
Next we start with
接下來我們就從
From the vantage point
違觀的角度來看
especially through
特別是透過
The mouths of these criminals in the file
檔案裡面這些犯罪者的口
Everyone states that they are so-called criminals
大家陳述自己是所謂犯罪
look at his criminal motives
來看他的犯罪動機
Then we will put some theories of this criminology
然後我們再把這個犯罪學的一些理論
time to analyze the motives of these crimes
來去分析這些犯罪動機的時候
you'll discover the theory of criminology
你就會發現犯罪學的理論
very effective in explaining the causes of crime in history
非常有效的來解釋歷史上的犯罪原因
First of all, there is a bias in criminology
首先犯罪學裡面有一個偏向
rational choice theory
經濟學角度的叫做理性抉擇論
That is to say, when ordinary people commit crimes
也就是說一般人在長教犯罪的時候
feel like I'm stealing
都會覺得我在偷竊的時候
The result will be better than my
得到的結果會比我
Now my situation is much better
現在自身的狀況要好很多的時候
I choose to steal
我才會選擇偷竊
This situation is used to explain
這種情況就用來解釋
Like Xia Li, a living poor person
像下立活生 貧困的人
Why would they choose to steal
他們為什麼會選擇偷竊
That's because they judged that the times they lived in were not good
那是因為他們估量到自己的生活時代不好
if we steal
如果我們偷竊的話
can make my life a little better
可以讓我的生活更好一點
This is called rational choice theory
這是叫做理性抉擇論
But then there is another problem
但是接下來就有另外一個問題
We will find a very interesting situation
我們會發現一個很有趣的狀況
when many poor people are stealing
就是很多窮人在偷竊的時候
he didn't steal alone
他不是一個人偷竊
he is a group host
他是一群人主持人
Kind of like a crime syndicate stealing
有點像是犯罪集團在偷竊
this is fun
這就好玩了
we actually see a lot
我們事實上看到很多
Confessions stolen by eighth-line party members
八線黨員偷竊的口供
Director Zhang San Wang Ermazi
張三理事 王二麻子
they are poor
他們都很窮
One day in the ruined temple
有一天在破廟裡面
suddenly everyone gathers together
大家突然聚集在一起
Discuss that everyone's life is so sad
商量說 大家的日子都那麼難過
Why don't we work together
乾脆我們一起來合作
to steal
去偷
And they'll all have a plan to steal
而且他們都會有計畫說去偷
Which family has silver at home?
哪一家的人家裡有銀子
So this according to social psychology
所以這個按照社會心理學
social aggregation theory
這叫做社會聚合論
That is to say
也就是說
when people are single
當人是單一的時候
your criminal
你的犯罪的
not so bold
沒有那麼大膽
But when you become a group of people
可是當你變成一群人的時候
you are getting bolder
你越來越有大膽
courage is getting bigger and bigger
膽子就越來越大了
social aggregation theory
這叫社會聚合論
The third one we talked about
第三個我們來談到了
except the poor steal
除了窮人會偷竊以外
some people are poor
還有一些人不窮
some people have careers
有些人會有職業
but why would he steal
可是他為什麼會偷竊
is related to the third
就是涉及到第三種
the theory of criminology
所謂犯罪學的理論
everyday life theory
叫日常生活理論
This theory of everyday life which states that
這個日常生活理論它指出
especially theft
特別是偷竊
Continue to have three elements
繼續要有三個要素
The first element, of course, is
第一個要素當然是
criminally inclined thief
有犯罪傾向的偷竊者
the second
第二個
you must have a goal
你必須要有目標
valuable stolen item
有價值的被偷竊的物品
the subject matter
這標的物
The third element is to have
第三個要素就是要有
In the absence of supervisors
監督者不在場的情況
That is to say, the combination of these three reasons
也就是說這三個原因合在一塊
crime will happen
就會發生犯罪
you have criminal tendencies today
你今天有個犯罪者傾向的人
you saw a valuable phone
你看到了一個有價值的手機
Then there was no one around
然後剛好四下無人
no one nor monitor
沒有任何人也沒有監視器
next thing you want to say
接下來你就會想說
This is a gift from God
這老天送給我的禮物
take it now
趕快拿走吧
let me steal
我偷吧
So this so-called opportunism
所以這種所謂的機會論
the theory of everyday life
就是日常生活理論
So we actually often see
所以我們其實常看到
a lot of thieves are like this
很多偷竊者是這樣子
special we iron tail says
特別我們鐵尾說
will mention cattle stealing
會提到偷牛的
Many people because of rural people
很多人因為農村人
After grazing the cattle, they put them in the countryside
都把牛放牧之後放在郊外
sometimes there are people
有時候就是有一些人
it ain't no work
它也不是沒有工作
it ain't without a job
它也不是沒有職業
it's not without income
它也不是沒有收入
But when it passed the paddy field
可是它經過稻田的時候
see the cow over there
看到的牛在那邊
no more manpower
又沒有了人手
And at this time feel
而這時候覺得
Just let me take the bull by the hand
乾脆我就順手牽牛
just took it away
就把它帶走了
In fact, there are many such cases
其實這種情況還是不少的
There are many cases of this
也有很多這個情況
I just saw it walking in the shops in this city
就是看到它走在這個都市裡面店鋪
Found the shop door open
發現店鋪門開的
in stock
裡面有貨
but no one is watching
但沒有人看手
It goes in and steals
它就進去偷東西了
So the situation is
所以這種情況是
This can explain the third
這個可以解釋第三種
But the fourth one is fun
但是第四種又很好玩
I want to explain
我要跟大家解釋
The fourth is to use this criminological theory
第四種是用這個犯罪學理
Called Situational Prevention Traveler Inside
叫情境預防旅人裡面
He mentioned that many criminals
他提到其實很多犯罪者
He is in a situation
他這是在一個情境下面
in everyday situations
在日常生活的情境下
Some are criminal motives
有的是犯罪的動機
especially if they are likely to be related by blood
特別是他們有可能血緣關係
with geographical or business relationship
有地緣關係或業緣關係的
as long as under the circumstances
只要在這種情況之下
a little chance
稍微有一點機會
is likely to encourage it to steal
才是可能就會促進它去偷竊
In terms of blood relationship
以血緣關係來講
The most common is that the son steals the father's money
最常見就是兒子偷老爸的錢
Geographical relations are neighbors
地緣關係裡面就是鄰居
Stealing a neighbor's money
一偷鄰居的錢
employee relations is
業員關係就是
Hired worker stealing from boss
僱傭的工人偷老闆的東西
This is a situation caused by a situation
這就是一種情境上面造成的一個情況
so this i say
所以這個我說
Why
為什麼
Spit gun is not necessarily
吐槍不一定是
No money
沒有錢
Maybe he has a business
說不定他是有資業
rich income
有錢 有收入
But it's possible to commit a crime
但一難有可能犯罪
that is
就是
this little house
這個小房子
At that time, this stupid thief stole the root
當時這個笨賊偷根
Because he sees if anyone is watching
因為他看到有沒有人看手
He secretly went to the city to sell
他就把偷偷到都市裡面賣
I probably know that the reason is so big once
就大概知道這個理由那麼大一次
Calibration is so large
標定度那麼大
So many people said
所以很多人當時就說
would rather steal a sheep
寧願偷一隻羊
don't steal a sheep
不要偷一隻羊
Next we look at this
接下來我們來看這個
Types of crime and the process of crime
犯罪的類型跟犯罪的過程
Generally we
一般我們
we say
我們說
like a beautiful one
就像一隻美麗那種
Bird tree for the enjoyment of skills
比技享受的鳥樹
we might think
我們可能會想
Wang Yi said
王毅說
This kind of nonsense
這種非子
pro-communist is very good
親共很好
this non
這個非子
is crime the norm
是不是犯罪的常態
so many crimes
那多少多少犯罪的
will be higher
會比較高呢
After these were stolen
這些偷了之後
Are they avenues with or without disassembly
它們是有沒有消裝的廣道
And are there some black hands behind them?
還有它們幕後是不是有些黑手
Well in fact
那麼事實上
We actually see
我們從實際來看到
Most of these fly the above
大部分這些飛的就是上述
In fact, not everyone knows
其實不見得大家也知道
It's not that hard to clean up
清工那麼難也不是
everyone practiced
大家都練成
Not every kid has a cleaner
不是每個小孩都有清工
then most often as a form of stealing
那麼最常成為偷竊行為的一種方式
is the so-called road pattern
是所謂的路勢形象
And the most commonly used way to find the image is
而且找路勢形象最常用就是
move the walls away
把牆壁招開來
That's what we see in this painting
就是我們看到這個畫裡面這些地
just inside the wall
就是著牆裡面
this is the most common
這是最常見的
In addition, theft is also common
另外爬竊也是常見的
There is another way we think
還有一種我們以為
only now
現在才有
In fact, there were gold plates in ancient times.
其實在古代就有金光板
Just use our famous cigarettes
就是用我們的名煙
That famous drug comes in the name of someone's theft
那樣名藥來名義人的偷竊
In fact, this can only appear in the bottom line
這個其實在底線也只能出現
Another thing is stealing
另外還有就是趁勢偷竊
It's the common practice of stealing things
就是順手偷東西的這個常見
But the most common one is actually road image
但是最常見的其實是路勢形象
next might be interesting
接下來可能有趣的
Hot funds that can be stolen many times
很多時候可能是偷竊的熱門基金
Usually it is the test base
通常就是考試的時候試子基
Exam period
考試考期
And when the market is open
還有市場開市感及的時候
Another one is when the wedding is followed.
還有一個就是婚禮跟接期的時候
This situation is actually at the meeting room
這個情況其實其實在臨滿場見房
Because many times the wedding photos are stolen
因為很多時候婚禮的時候照相偷
In addition, when these thieves are arrogant, how can they be arrogant?
另外囂張的時候這些小偷怎麼囂張
Knots as part of more experienced thieves
結當部分比較有經驗的小偷
They will analyze the things that steal drugs to be arrogant
他們會把偷藥的東西分析去囂張
He won't be arrogant all the time
他不會一直去囂張
Because he knows that the goal of being arrogant all the time is too low-level
因為他知道一直囂張目標太低級
So where could he be arrogant?
那麼他可能去哪裡囂張呢
He may go to the pawnshop to be a pawn
他可能去當戶裡面去當
He may go to the market and set up a stall in those markets to sell directly
他可能去市場直接在那些市場擺攤去賣
he may also sell directly to the checkout
他也可能直接賣給結帳者
said to take care of
是說過照顧的
Then let's look at
那麼接下來我們來看
Is there a so-called black hand behind the scenes?
有沒有所謂幕後的黑手呢
It was called my home in the post office at that time
是在當時的郵用叫做我這家
The explanation is called Wojia
解釋叫窩家
And these nests usually open inns
而且這些窩家通常都是開設客棧
open an inn
開設客棧
So those officials feel
所以那些官員都覺得
The best way to develop this nest
要研製這種窩家最好的方法
Even Baojia and the law
就連保甲和法律
Use this method to lift up these innkeepers
用這個方法去自抬這些開客棧的人
because of their
因為他們的
You see, the inn is also an inn
你看這客棧人也是客棧
is big or small
是大小小的
If you use the law to make an appointment with Baojia
如果是用法律跟保甲去約識這些
The so-called opening an inn and becoming a home
所謂開客棧成為窩家
This is an important crime prevention method
這是一個重要的防治犯罪的方法
ok so next question
好 那麼接下來問一個問題
what kind of person is easy to be stolen
什麼樣的人容易被偷
Do you think rich people are easy to be stolen?
大家覺得是有錢的人容易被偷嗎
actually not
其實不是
our current statistics
我們現在的統計
This is my statistic from the answer
這是我從答案裡面的統計出來
You can know
你們可以知道
Most of the stolen ones were merchants
被偷的裡面最多是商人
In fact, generations of scientists
其實是世代科學者
and some workers
還有一些工人
In fact, those who are really rich in this so-called co-existing drama
其實真正有錢的這種所謂的相生劇的這些
In fact, it adds up to less votes
其實它加起來比較少被投
So we say that most people will be voted
所以我們說其實大部分人會被投
They're all so-called middle-class families.
都是所謂的中產之家
or Chinese House
或中文的之家
So how many people are there in Chinese House and Chinese House?
那麼中文之家跟中文之家大概有多少錢人
According to the status at that time, there were probably more than 100 taels
按照當時的地位大概是有100兩以上
how much is it
大概是多少錢人
Not more than 100 taels
不是有100兩以上
And then less than 1000 taels of such a moment
然後不到1000兩的這樣的論矩
so-called middle-class home
資產的所謂的中產之家
Then if you have more than 1000 taels
那如果你從過1000兩以上
was recognized at that time
對當時就被地位承認
1000 taels are responsible
有1000兩是負責的
So let's look at the voted
所以我們看看這些被投的
Probably Chinese House
大概都是中文之家
In fact, when the democrats
其實在民進的時候
At that time, many people already realized that
當時其實已經有很多人認識到這個
So many opinions say
所以很多觀點都說
When the bandits come
小道小匪一來的話
The most vulnerable is the so-called Chinese House
最容易受害的就是所謂的中文之家
Then these Chinese homes
那麼這些中文之家
Will they choose to report to the police?
他們會不會選擇報官呢
In fact, in traditional Chinese
其實在中國傳統的時候
There are also many people who say that the reporter
也有很多人說報官
become a black art
就變成一種黑術
So the criminal's black art is in some
所以犯罪者的黑術在一些
market appears
市場出現
And there are many
而且數量也不少
So these things I said today
所以我今天說的這些東西
Actually true is not really the number of possible
其實真正是不是真的發生的數量可能
much higher than these
遠遠高過這些數量
Then why did they report to the police?
那他們為什麼報官呢
There are also several reasons
也有幾種原因
Sometimes because of the pulled
有時候因為被pull的這個
actually every time
每次其實
we see actual cases
我們看到實際的案件
Every time it is pulled
每一次被pull的
The value of that thing is actually not that high
那個東西的價值其實都不高
except for a few
除了少部分
It will exceed dozens of taels of silver
會超過幾十兩的銀子
or this for up to a hundred people
或最多一百人的這個
Most of the silver
那大部分的銀兩
Most of these silver taels that were pulled
大部分被pull的這些銀兩
They are actually only one tael or two taels of silver
都是其實只有一兩或二兩銀子
Then for the middle class data
那麼對於中產資料來講
Actually such value
其實這樣的價值
such this
這樣的這個
such a price
這樣的這個物價
or such a value
或者說這樣的價值
It's actually not that big of a loss.
對它來講其實損失不算太大
So usually they may choose to report to the official
所以通常他們可能會選擇報官
depends on them
就看他們
The reason for their customs declaration this time is because
他們這次報關的原因是因為
sometimes at the end of sleep
有時候發生在睡末
winter time
冬天的時候
Because the government is at the end of his sleep
因為官府他在睡末的時候
He does not accept reports
他是不接受報案
so even if it happens
所以即使發生了
You went to report the crime and he didn't accept it.
你去報案也沒有理他不接
So sometimes many cases
所以有時候很多案件
In fact, at the end of sleep
其實在睡末的時候
He actually became a criminal melanin
他其實變成一種犯罪黑素
Another possibility is
另外還有一種可能是
in the process of reporting
在報案的過程中
many victims he felt
很多受害者他覺得
his risk is higher
他的風險更高
because no matter from the countryside
因為不論從鄉村
or to the city's platform
或到城市的平台
in the countryside
在鄉村的時候
sometimes you take a long time
有時候你要花很長的時間
get the door now
到現拿門
In the middle, there are actually considerable risks
在中間其實也有相當的風險
And it costs a lot
而且花的這個成本很高
Not necessarily after customs declaration
也不見得報關之後
you can really get it back
你真的可以拿回來
with the original header item
以原來的頭前物品
Therefore, many people think that it is not a declaration
所以也有很多人覺得是不報關
This is the cause of many criminal melanin administration
這都是造成很多犯罪黑素行政的原因
Plus everyone knows
再加上大家心裡也知道
I also analyzed earlier
我前面也分析
Only a 28% detection rate
只有28%的破案率
think about it
大家想想看
You are the master of ten, so your case has been dragged by this extreme tree
你作為十主,那你的案你被拖了這個極量木子
Then your family lives far away from Xinshan, Xinshan
那麼又是你家裡又住的離信山,信山很遠
Think about it, forget it, the reporting officer may not have actually done a case
想一想,算了,報告官也不見得真的做了個案
So most of them will probably choose the reporting officer
所以大部分可能都會選擇報告官
what are we going to see next
那接下來我們來看什麼東西
Thieves love to drag
小偷最愛拖
A few days ago I was talking to an Israeli friend about this time
前幾天我跟我一個以色列的朋友聊到這一次
I guessed with him, saying that he is doing Buddhism
我就跟他猜,說他是做佛教
I said you guess
我說你猜猜看
what is most often dragged
什麼樣東西最常被拖
And the jewelry, right?
而且那珠寶啊對不對
I said no
我說不是
I said cows, I said cows, there are many cows, but not the most
我說牛,我說牛是牛不少,但是不是最多
but he said what is it
但是他說這是什麼東西
I said that the person who is most often dragged is
我說其實最常被拖的人是
clothes, clothes are the most often dragged
衣服,衣服是最常被拖的
Then this clothes being dragged is not a Chinese characteristic
那這個衣服被拖不是中國的特色
It's the same in Europe
其實在歐洲也是一樣
Clothes were the most frequently dragged in Britain and France in early modern Europe
近代早期歐洲的英國、法國最常被拖的就是衣服
so why are the clothes dragged
所以衣服為什麼被拖
The most common passive is actually related to consumption
最常被動其實說在跟消費有關
In fact, this East and West in the early modern
其實這個東西方在近代早期
fashion of things
東西形成的時尚
especially consumer clothes
特別是消費的衣服
One more form of fashion
多一種形式的時尚
So many people steal clothes and sell them better
所以很多人偷衣服最好賣
Because the most people want it
因為連用最多人要嘛
So why should we talk about a US-Taiwan
所以為什麼該談到一支美台
Run to New York Road to steal clothes
跑去New York Road偷衣服
from a
來自於一位
That's because it's so good at cooking
那是因為它非常好消灶
and very nice
而且非常好氣感
Actually operating gas
其實是經營氣體
like camp
比如說像營館
camp meals these snacks
營餐這些零食品
very easy to burn
非常好消灶的
easy to steal
好偷的也好帶
In addition, daily necessities
另外就是日常用品
originally deep class
本來深處類
Like cows, chickens, ducks and other deep species
像牛啊 雞啊 鴨這些深處類
in the eighteenth century in the former east
在十八世紀在前東時候
The ratio of being stolen is quite high.
被偷的比例還蠻高的
But in the nineteenth century
但是到了十九世紀中
The proportions stolen from these depths of agriculture
這些農業的這些深處被偷的比例
lower a lot
就降低很多
because the reason is very simple
因為理由很簡單
because rich people
因為有錢的人
people with money
會有錢的人
Can not be regarded as concentrated in the city
不可以當作集中在都市裡面
So most thieves start asking for
所以大部分的小偷人都開始要
if he chooses to spit
如果他要選擇吐東西的話
He will choose something that is easier to carry and more valuable
他會選擇更容易帶價值更高的東西
Most of those are in the city
那些大部分都是在都市裡面
Then I said just now that when I reported the crime
然後我剛才說其實在報案的時候
He'll make a poem list of what he's ripping
他會把自己撕竊的東西寫成詩單
This is one of the poetry lists at that time
這就當時的詩單的一個東西
He'll say what he tore up for himself
他會說給他自己撕竊的什麼東西
You still have to pretend that there are a lot of Chinese words written in the city
你還要當裡面很多寫著都市的漢語
And Xiaoyi
還有小衣
and hat
還有帽子
In fact, sheep shops in the clothing category are the most frequently listed
其實服飾類的羊鋪都是最常被列聽的
It's the most frequent thief on this cruise.
就是最常小偷的這場郵輪
There is also this horse maniac below
下面也是還有這個馬狂
and cloth
還有布
These can't be seen
這些不可以看出來
There are also casual men
還有散男
So we can see here
所以我們這裡可以看得出來
This is when these clothes
這是在當初這些衣服
why everyday language is so good
日常用語之所以非常好
There are actually a lot of sheep shops in there.
那裡面其實還有很多羊鋪
For example, these sheep shops
比如說這些羊鋪
The things on the shoulders are some sheep shop
衣膀的東西都是一些羊鋪
You can see this sheep shop here
這裡可以看到這個羊鋪
in the wild
在中野之中
In China, it is actually very immortal
在中國其實非常地不滅
There's actually something in there
裡面其實還有些東西
i didn't list it
我沒有列出來
especially some cultural goods
特別是有一些文化商品
cultural goods
文化商品
Don't talk about Yantai
別說燕台
And very high-grade wood
還有很高級的木
and Shuhua
還有舒化
These things are actually found inside
這些東西其實在裡面都有看到
But from inside we can see these cultural goods
但從裡面我們可以看到這些文化商品
is a drifter
是流流者
It's the benefactor
就是它背透的施主
In fact, it doesn't have to be a senior official.
其實並不是一定是高官
But it's definitely something called citizenship
但是它絕對是有所謂的公民身份一些事人
So these cultural goods
所以這些文化商品
In fact, these people
其實是這些事人
A symbolic way of wanting to follow its identity and taste
想跟它身份品味的一種象徵路
these problems are there
這些問題都在那裡
but which are the richest
但是最有錢是哪些
stolen richest
被偷的最有錢的
actually an official
其實是官員
Because for the top consumption
因為針對消費頂端
This tradition is really consuming top things
這傳統是真的消費頂端的東西
is advanced
是高級的
So we see a max coffee steal
所以我們看到一個最大咖啡偷的
It's actually a matter of design
其實是一個設計的問題
ok , so let ' s take another look at the cities
好,那麼,另外我們來看一下都市
We're discussing the biggest relationship this crime firm has with the city.
我們在討論這個犯罪所跟都市最大的關係
It's about discussing which places are most prone to crime
就是討論哪一些地方最容易發生犯罪
These so-called crime hotspots, crime problems
這些所謂的犯罪熱點,犯罪的問題
I have a friend who studies Shanghai
我有一個研究上海的朋友
He studied Shanghai's Little Britain period through
他研究上海的小英國時期透過來
He found that, crawling hands, the most common case of crawling hands
他發現那個,爬手啊,最常發生爬手的案件
all concentrated at the intersection of the road
都集中在馬路的交叉
ok , that ' s a road cross
好,就是馬路交叉
Like running away after stealing something
比如是偷了東西之後馬上跑
Because he has many routes to choose from
因為他有很多可以選擇跑的路線
less easy to catch
比較不容易可以抓到
Let's take a look at this and see that the case happened in a traditional city.
那我們來看看這個見到案件發生在傳統的城市裡面
What areas can everyone enter
大家可以進入到哪些地區
Of course I didn't study as detailed as my friend
當然我沒有像我那個朋友研究那麼細
Then I use this picture of Chongqing
然後我用這個重慶的圖
This is the city map of Chongqing in the Qing Dynasty at that time
這是當時清朝化的重慶的城市圖
Then we update this to get Chongqing
那麼我們更新這個可以得出來重慶
At that time, his in various regions
當時各個地區的他的這個
access his function
訪他的功能
like this block in blue
像藍色的這個區塊
is the business district
就是商業區
red block
紅色這個區塊
is the administrative area
就是行政區
like this block is the parish
像這個區塊是中教區
So we just had a little talk with God
所以我們剛才稍微天主談談
The place between these temples
這種廟子之間的那個地方
this is the transport zone
這個是運輸區
because there are many piers
因為這裡很多碼頭
Then this is the so-called stone pipe
然後這是所謂的石管
because later this
因為後來這個
After the opening of the five-port trade
五口通商開管之後
There are a lot of places between the stone pipes
這裡有很多石管之間的地方
then let's see
那麼我們看看
next picture
接下來這張圖
This picture is to see this cut to the case
這張圖就是看這個切到案件
Which spaces are the longest among them
最長其中在哪一些空間
we see the darkest
我們看到顏色最深的
more than fifty
就是五十件以上
Orthodox and Orthodox and Orthodox
正經與正經與正經
But these two areas
偏偏這兩個區域
In fact, it is a business district and an administrative district.
其實就是商業區和行政區
So in traditional cities
所以在傳統的城市裡面
Cut to the longest of the cases
切到案件最長其中的
Is in the business district and administrative district
是在商業區與行政區
this is the case
是這個情況
I think when going to the end
我想在進入到末尾的時候
i want to discuss
我想討論一下
In the Qing Dynasty, the way of cutting
到底在清朝對於切割的方式
how does it work
它效果怎麼樣
We can use this criminology master He
我們可以用這個犯罪學的賀主理
Talk about discussing three criteria to see the situation at that time
說討論三個標準去看當時的情況
This is called the relationship of principle
這個叫做原理性的關係
that is to say in the city
也就是說在城市
way cities when these cut categories
方式 城市這些切割分類的時候
Its laws, the rule of law, are strict enough
它的法律 法治夠夠嚴厲
In fact, through the previous discussion, we
我們其實透過前面的討論
already visible
已經可以看到
Actually, I think it's something that can't be said
其實我覺得是講不過的事情
Yeah
是嗎
right
對
sound is great
聲音都是大的效果
so i think there is also
所以我覺得也有
I think in terms of severity
我覺得在嚴厲性的角度
We can see the green beauty in the Qing Dynasty
我們可以看到在大清綠麗
Whether it is green or beautiful
不論是綠麗也好
Luli is also good
綠麗也好
In fact, the specification for cutting
其實對於切割的規範
and come true are very subtle
和成真都是非常細微
So in terms of severity
所以從嚴厲性來講
OK, he has such an effect
OK,是他具有這樣的效果
But then the swiftness
但是接下來迅速性
what is rapidity
什麼叫迅速性
In modern terms, it is called quick trial and quick decision
用句現代的話叫做速審速決
Which means after today's crime
也就是說今天發生的犯罪之後
you caught the criminal
你抓到了犯人
Is it going to be a quick trial?
是不是要很快速審速決
But we see a lot of these suspects get caught
偏偏我們看到很多這些嫌疑犯抓到之後
In fact, your case still can't be used later.
事實上你的案件還是沒辦法隨後使出
Why? Because many cases are in the process of expedited trial and trial
為什麼?因為很多案件在速審跟審理的過程
took a long time
花了很長時間
Sometimes these cuts to the suspect
有時候這些切到犯罪的嫌犯
After being caught, he said that he had an accomplice
抓了之後他就說他有同伙是隨隨隨
Then we can't catch those accomplices anyway
那麼總之抓不到那些同伙
I feel like this case has been extended and there is no way to solve it.
就覺得這個案子就一直延大沒辦法解案
So there is a little bit of a problem in terms of speed.
所以就迅速性來講也是有一點問題
As for what this certainty refers to
至於這個確定性指的是什麼
that is to say a criminal
也就是說一個犯罪者
When a crime can be sure soon
當犯罪之後能夠很確定很快的
suffered rumors
就遭受到陰謠
this punishment
這個懲罰
But we also saw earlier
可是我們前面也看到
In fact, to be honest
其實切道案來講
So its detection rate is 28 percent
它的破案率所以有百分之二十八
That is to say, more than 80% of people who commit crimes cannot be caught.
也就是說有百分之八十幾人犯罪是抓不到
it can escape
它可以逃
it can get away with it
它可以逍遙法外
Then from this certainty, it is not enough
那從這個確定性來講它是不夠
So from this point of view
所以從這個角度來看
The Qing Dynasty as a whole was at least sustaining its own business
清朝整個至少在持久自己中業
it's in the punitive crime
它在犯罰切道犯罪裡面
even though it has strict regulations
即使它有很嚴厲的法規
But it can't tell the truth
但是它沒辦法述是述是決
Its detection rate is also very limited
它的破案率也非常有限
So take the protection of China
所以套取中國這個保護
So-called local law cannot be enforced
叫做土法不能以執行
you continue to have the law
你繼續有法律
You can't really have these mechanisms related to the housing market
你沒辦法確確的有這相關的房市的這些機制
Such a law is still empty
這樣的法律還是空的
no way housing market true crime
沒辦法房市真正的犯罪
That's what I'm going to do for you today
以上就是我今天給大家做的方法
Welcome everyone to listen to advice
歡迎大家聽聽指教
thank you all
謝謝大家
I think when everyone heard this story just now, it was very vivid and interesting.
我想剛才大家都聽到這個故事的時候非常生動有趣的意思
I think we, the audience, have questions. If you ask questions, welcome to ask them at this time.
我想我們這個有聽眾有問題的話提問的話歡迎這個時候提出來
Does anyone want to ask some further questions?
到底有沒有人想進一步問一些問題
well, this gentleman is at the end
好,這位先生在最後
Okay, Im sorry, thats what I just wanted to do in the process
好,這位不好意思,就是我之前總共一點剛剛就是要像過程裡面
That is to say, there are some disruptions in the market or the situation that the teacher just mentioned is early and strong.
就是說在市場中有一些破壞充斥或是老師有剛剛講到早強的狀況
Is that the markets in various cities during the climax just now?
那是不是剛才在情潮的時候的各個城市他們的市場
Does their house look like a phenomenon?
他們的這個房子是不是都很像有現象
Thanks
謝謝
"Cao Chao Traveler"
《曹超旅人》
The villain is called Weasley Slatto
反派人叫做魏斯里史萊圖
And there's a scene in it that's Wesley Slaytoo
那其中有個橋段是魏斯里史萊圖
when he arrives in the future
他到了未來的時候
He wants to test the power of future police policing
他想測試一下未來的警察治安的力量
He saw a car on the street
他就在街上看到一個車子
He knocked on that car window
他就敲那個車窗
He figured he had the police coming
他就估計他有警察會來
After a long time, the police still haven't come
結果過了很久警察還沒來
He knocks on the second window
他就敲第二個車窗
forget it
再算了
not yet
還不來
He said he was too good
他說他也太好了
this is my heaven
這個真是我天堂
is my crime paradise
就是我犯罪的天堂
This is actually another crime theory.
這其實就是另外一種犯罪理論
present in the movie
在電影裡面呈現
But I think the broken gut theory makes sense
但是我覺得破腸理論很有道理
But used in the history of Ming and Qing Dynasties
但是用在明清的歷史
Especially in terms of the history of the Qing Dynasty
特別清朝的歷史來講
more difficult to use
比較難用
Because to be honest, this gut-breaking theory
因為說實在的這個破腸理論
is a very modern theory
是一個非常現代的理論
very modern theory
非常現代的理論
Especially in modern urbanized buildings
尤其是在現代的都市化的建築
will use
才會用
This traditional Chinese building
中國傳統的這個建築
buildings in the city
在城市裡面建築
Actually window
其實窗
There are few windows in the city
在城市裡面窗很少
because most of the computer
因為大部分是電腦
So the computer arrives this evening
所以電腦到了這個晚上
It's actually made of wood planks to keep the wind up.
它其實都是用木板把風起來的
So usually when you go to steal a computer
所以通常那去偷電腦的時候
you have to use another method
你要用其他方法
just put it that
就是把它那個
this is one way
這是一種方法
The second way is to climb the wall
第二種方法就是爬牆
climb to the second floor of it
爬到它二樓
Because the first floor of the traditional Chinese shop
因為中國傳統的店鋪一樓
it is two layers
它是兩層
Chinese traditional shop is two floors
中國傳統店鋪是兩層樓
The first floor is sealed with wooden boards
一層樓它是用木板把它封起來
When the official gate is sealed with wooden boards
官門的時候用木板封起來
But there are windows on the second floor
但是二樓有窗戶
call skylight
叫天窗
So the second way is you climb the skylight
所以第二種方法就是你爬天窗
Go to the second floor to draw the machine
到二樓去抽中機
So many shops were stolen
所以很多店鋪被竊了
Usually in addition to being knocked into the pot by the wall
通常除了被牆被敲鍋之外
is knocking on the door
就是門被敲起來
Someone climbed to the skylight
還有有人爬到天窗
Go in through the skylight on the second floor to smoke something
從二樓的天窗進去裡面去抽東西
So why didn't I use the inside of the broken window
所以為什麼我沒有用破窗裡面
The reason is because there is no suitable
理由就是因為沒有適合
Because there is a more modern version of this objection in the broken window
因為破窗裡面有一個比較現代的這種反對
So in the traditional Chinese period
所以在中國傳統時期
There is no way to explain it this way
比較沒辦法用這個方法去解釋
Because the traditional Chinese architecture was different at that time
因為當時中國傳統建築型態不太一樣
so it counts
所以它算是
That's it, thank you
就是這樣,謝謝
lady please sit down
這位女士,請坐
May I ask, was Xiao Cong a local at that time?
問一下,那個年代的小聰是當地人嗎?
ok very good please sit down please sit down
好,非常好,請坐,請坐
In fact, I say this, you Chongqing as an example
其實我這樣說,你重慶作為例子
In fact, why is urbanization so serious?
其實為什麼都市化那麼嚴重
I would ask why the urbanization is growing so fast in 19
我會問為什麼在19近都市化一下是增長那麼快
In fact, urbanites are not particularly good at living
其實並不是都市人特別會生
No, urbanites are especially good at giving birth, and there are so many children at once
不是,都市人特別會生,生小孩一下變得那麼多
In fact, most of them are foreigners who came here to find work and do business.
其實大部分是外地人跑來從近找工作做生意
So most of them are foreigners
所以大部分是外地人
Well, actually head inside, and then build the hut inside
那麼其實頭到裡面,後建裡面的小屋
There is quite a field house
有相當的一個是外地屋
quite a field
相當的一個外地
The proportion of local discoveries is certainly not low
本地發現的比例,當然也不是說很低欄
But for the first time I said there might be half etiquette too
但是我第一次說可能也有半個禮儀
Other counties and cities
外縣市
I can't count
我沒辦法統計
Because there was no way to do this statistics at that time.
因為當時已經沒辦法做這個統計
but we say for sure
但是我們肯定說
People from other counties and cities
外縣市來的人
As a child's travel port high
作為小時候的旅運口高
And what?
而且呢
i mentioned earlier
我前面提到了
Many were poor when they were young
有很多小時候是窮人
then get together
然後聚在一塊
Everyone started to vote
大家開始投到的
in that case
那種情況之下
Many of these people are foreigners
很多這些人都是外地人
are foreigners
都是外地人
because of the words of the locals
因為本地人的話
he usually doesn't follow
他通常不會跟
Not so many people gather together
不會有那麼多人聚集在一塊
usually foreigners
通常都是外地人
Find those crackpots and get together over there
找那些破妙在那邊聚集在一起
Therefore, the travel port of foreigners is high.
所以外地人的旅運口高
But this will lead to
但是這就會牽制到
The first is actually something that modern criminology pays great attention to.
第一個其實現代犯罪學非常注意的
A problem of great concern in criminology
現在犯罪學非常注意的一個問題
that is
也就是
Immigration is a disruption of social order
移民是破壞社會秩序
an important information
一個重要的資料
Of course the immigration
當然現在講的移民
Comparison is no longer imaging immigrants
比較已經不是成像移民
more like immigrant
比較像是外國移民
Immigrants from other provinces
外省移民
but
不過
The perspective of traditional officials
傳統官員的角度
They do feel that aliens are coming
他們的確會覺得外地來臨
dangerous
是危險分子
But they will also know that they can't call out the translator all at once
但是他們也會知道不能一竿子把翻譯調出來
Because in fact, many people from other places come to do business
因為其實有很多外地來的人是來做生意
or they have a professional job
或他們是有職業工作
so this
所以這個
So the official
所以當時這個官員
one thing they must say
他們一定會講的一件事
Chongqing this place
重慶這個地方
Wufang Zazu
五方雜祖
What's the meaning
什麼意思
It's from all over the place
就是各地來的都有
So easy to grow and work
所以容易長兼職業
things are vague
講的東西很模糊
mean to say
意思就是說
Chongqing because many people from other places do business here
重慶因為很多外地來的民民在這邊做生意
So there are also many big buyers
所以裡面長夫大購者也不少
There are quite a few people who come to the world to touch
有人來國際摸摸的也不少
Master thinks this means
大師長覺得這個意思
So the father of information or current management
所以當時的資訊或現管之父
Actually realize these things
其實也意識到這些事情
So we still have to implement
所以我們還是必須落實到
who is supporting
到底支持的人是什麼人
So under this circumstance, I can answer you, the proportion of outside points is actually quite high, which is equal to how many times the proportion reaches this time, it is difficult to estimate
所以在這個情況之下,我能回答你,外點的比例其實請教派對女生蠻高的,等於這次比例到多少次,很難估計的事
hope to answer you
希望能夠回答你
Thank you, Ms. Bai Yurure, are you familiar with it?
謝謝這位白玉如熱女士,您是不是聽熟了?
i heard what do you think
我聽聞你怎麼看
What do you think, first in US M crams
請問您怎麼看,先在 US M crams
In the store, I ask you to search
店裡面,叫你搜檢
output this now'll
輸出這個現'll
Grab steep C mass ai
搶陡C mass ai
Looking at the street will return to the old days
把對看在套街會還昔日
Could you please check
請問您可以搜檢
The data searched is
搜檢的資料是
$950
$950
is $500
是$500
you can search
您可以搜檢
search
搜檢
What do you think
你怎麼看
well , actually your question is very meaningful
好,其實你的問題非常有意義
very interesting
非常有意思
But since you ask the question now is the question now
但是因為你現在問問題是現在的問題
I put this problem in the Qing Dynasty
我把這樣的問題放到清朝來看
The Qing Dynasty, especially the issue you mentioned later
清朝特別是你後面提到的這個問題
In this way, I may not be able to answer your previous questions.
這樣我前面問題可能沒辦法回答你
But the problem behind you is
可是你後面的問題就是
For example, now there are many refugees
比如說現在有很多流民到一些
he might grab something
他可能順手拿一些東西
he may not feel that he
他可能不覺得說他
What do you know about Xiao Bingmo
你知道蕭兵墨什麼
grab something
順手拿一些東西
He may not think he is gay
他可能不覺得他是同性
But it was like this when I was a child
但是小時候有這樣的情況
that there is an objection in tradition
那在傳統有一個反對
social objection
按照反對學程叫做社會性反對
What is social opposition
什麼叫社會性反對
so
這樣
in traditional Chinese
在中國傳統的時候
Our general family will only go outside the iron
我們一般人家只會到鐵以外
There may be some mountains nearby
附近大概會有一些山
some mountains
有些山
There will be wood down the mountain
到山下都會有木材
common people think
一般人老百姓覺得
I go to the nearby mountains
我去附近的山上
cut trees, cut moss
砍樹木、砍苔
it's not illegal
這是不犯法的
social crime
這叫社會性犯法
but
但是呢
in fact not necessarily so
事實上不一定這樣
because at that time
因為在那個時候
woods on many hills or these
很多山上的樹林或這些
it is kind
它是有種的
so
所以
that's how it's generally said
就是一般這樣說
there are many people when
有很多人當
So in the Qing Dynasty
所以在清朝來講
Even when it was Trump
就算是川普的時候
some people he thinks
有一些人他覺得
he took something today
他今天拿一些東西
i do something
我做一些事情
Does not involve legal same-sex issues
不會涉及到法律同性的問題
But legally speaking
但是在法律來講
He's actually gay
他其實就是同性
So that means
所以就是說
a matter of habit
這一種習慣的問題
That is to say, you follow the wind is a habit today
就是說你今天按照風屬習慣
he thinks
他覺得說
giving some example
在舉某種例子
I'm following a certain wind habit
我在按照某種風屬習慣
I went through a today
我今天經過了一個
land
陸上
see this
看到這個
There are apples and orange barrels on the nearby tree
旁邊的樹上有蘋果,有橘子桶
There is a conceptual contradiction
有一個觀念上的矛盾
some people think it's a habit
有些人認為它是一個習慣
it does not involve legal issues
它不涉及到法律的問題
But legally it's a steal
但是從法律來講它是一個偷竊
It involves you stealing someone's belongings
它會涉及到你偷了人家的物品
all items
所有的物品
There will be such a contradictory character
會有這樣的矛盾的性格存在
Happens in many things whether present or traditional
偏偏在很多不論現在或傳統的事情
This notion is sometimes
這種觀念其實有時候會有
Some contradictions and overlaps
一些矛盾跟交錯的情況
so that it will cause
以至於就會造成
inside the objection
反對的行為裡面
The person involved really thinks he is a criminal
當事人他很認他是犯罪
Because he is in his traditional concept
因為他在他的傳統觀念裡面
He thinks his stuff is from himself
他覺得他那些就是自來的東西
His so-called social crimes
他那些叫社會性犯罪
Then what do you say about this thing?
那你說這個東西要怎麼樣去
For example, I said how to change
比如我說怎麼去改變
It's actually hard for me to answer Li Zhi's question
我其實很難回答李智的問題
Because this according to historians also
因為這個按照歷史學家的也就
not a chinese historian
不是中國歷史學家
is a historian of european studies
是歐洲研究歷史學家
criminal history
有專門研究犯罪史
study this so-called social crime
研究這個所謂社會性犯罪
He thinks that many behaviors
他覺得其實很多行為
Traditionally, it is not a crime
在傳統裡面習慣來講都不是犯罪
But because a few rich people
但是因為少數的有錢人
In order to protect his assets
他為了要保護自己的資產
He gives power to the law
他給定力來法律
make these behaviors
讓這些行為都變成了
crimes against the property of vietnamese people
親越人家財產的犯罪
So the process of law formation
所以法律形成過程
There are a lot of vested interests
有很多其實是有就是既得利
or a mechanism set up by the rich to protect himself
或者有錢的人所設立保護他自己的一種機制
Then many ordinary people and their families are easy to offend when they dont know about it.
那麼很多老百姓及家不知道的時候就容易觸犯
But his own person is not a crime
但他本身的人那不是犯罪才是
In terms of European history, there are such studies
這在歐洲的歷史來講是有這樣的研究
However, such research may draw criticism from other scholars.
不過這樣的研究可以引起另外一些學者的批評
That is, how do you know the criminals and their confessions
就是說你怎麼知道那些犯罪者他們口供
say we know i thought it was tradition
說我們知道我以為這是傳統
This is possible
這是可以的
How can you be sure that the reason these people are giving is not an excuse
你怎麼能夠確定這些人所講的理由不是一種藉口
In other words, he deliberately found an excuse
也就是說他也是故意找出一個藉口
So he clearly knew it was a crime
所以他明明知道是犯罪
he found an excuse
他找出一個藉口
This is actually a bit like many communication people in China want to steal
這其實有點像中國的很多通信的人想偷
He actually stole something he'd been stealing for maybe 50 years
他其實偷了可能他偷了50年的東西
Might actually ask him how much you stole
可能真的問他說你偷了多少東西
how much did you steal like this
你偷了多少這樣子
He just said I stole a little bit
他只說我偷了一點點
I stole everything else
其他都是我偷的
Because he if I come out
因為他如果我公出來
he stole it all
都是他偷的
then not the most followed
然後不是最有跟著的
then he might say
然後他可能說
He also didn't steal it from me
他也要都不是我偷
are stolen
都是別人偷
Or I just picked it up
或者是我順手拿的
i don't know what this is
我並不知道這個是怎麼樣
or some people
或者說有一些人
he accepts a dirt
他接受一個髒物
pick up dirt these people
接髒物這些人
buy dirt these people
買髒物這些人
then he will say
那麼他會變成說
i didn't know it was dirt
我不知道這是髒物
But I still spent so much money to buy
可是我還花了那麼多錢去買
good
好
This is my current unit
這是我現關的單位
How is it usually found that such a situation
現關通常發現這樣的情況是怎麼樣
his method of punishment
他的處罰方法
In fact it's still too early
事實上還是太早了
That is to say, those who take the dirt
也就是說那些拿髒物的人
Although you become saying
你雖然變成說
i didn't know it was dirt
我不知道這是髒物
But you still have to put the dirt in a root
但是你還是要把髒物放一個根本
so the guy who bought the dirt
所以買髒物的那個人
whether he knows or not
不論是他知道或不知道
I know when I'm gone
走了也知道
finally got caught
最後被抓到手
you are not worth the principle
你不貴於原則
going back
就要回頭
So according to the actual marriage of the Seven Dynasties and the appearance of the bookstore
所以按照七朝這實際判婚和書店的這個樣子
I hope a little bit will answer some of your questions
我希望有點能夠回答你的一些問題
But because my research is history
不過因為我研究是歷史
Contemporary issues may be more appropriate for contemporary qualifications
當代的問題可能比較適合當代的學歷
Hope to answer some of your questions
希望能夠回答你的一些
Thanks
謝謝
Then this classmate first ask Cai Yunfeng
那這個同學先問蔡允豐
Hello Professor
教授你好
then i have two questions
那我有兩個問題
The first question is about the criminal data and documents mentioned above.
第一個問題就是像是前面提到的犯罪數據跟文書的
It is clearer than Qianlong's arrival
比乾隆朝到很清楚
It is the words of the seven dynasties from the front to the back
就是七朝前起到後起的話
His data is slowly increasing
他的數據是慢慢增加
That number is because
那這樣的數字是因為
The more you go to the region and modern or modern
越到區域與現代或者是近代的話
Then his documents will be better preserved.
那他文書保存會比較好
That's why the majority
所以才比較多數
The second question is
那第二個問題就是
Like ancient times, whether it is the Qing Dynasty or earlier
像是古代不管是清代或是在更以前的話
That kind of comparison details
那這種比較細節
Then folk clerical data
然後民間的文書數據
If he
那他如果
take this secret
採用這個機密的話
that is
就是
For example, in local government offices
比如說在地方的官府衙門
still say yes
還是說會
Send it from the beginning to the center to keep it
從頭送到中央去做保住
because
因為
i would like to say
我會想說
If you do research later
如果後事做研究的話
He'll need some data and facts
他會需要一些數據跟實料
then he will come out of him
那他會出自於他
ok thanks professor
好 謝謝教授
very good question
非常好的問題
Apparently this gentleman has quite an understanding of this stuff
顯然這位先生對這個東西有相當的理解
Actually it is
其實是這樣
In these judicial files leaked by the local Zhou
地方上的周洩的這些司法檔案裡面
He is roughly divided into two
他大概分成兩
For example, we can roughly divide it into two
比如說我們初略可以分成兩種
Two categories of this justice
兩類的這個司法
sin of crime
犯罪的罪
intermarriage iron
一類的叫做互婚鐵
probably
大概就是
so-called marriage-related
所謂跟婚姻有關的
It's related to the division of this land.
跟這個土地就分有關的這類的
Half of this type of intermarriage
這類的互婚鐵有一半
now let's talk
現在我們來講
may be inferior to so-called civil cases
可能比較遜於所謂民事案件
this civil case
這種民事案件
Usually its OK after Zhou Xieguan finishes the sentence
通常就在周洩關自己判完就OK了
he doesn't have to report to that
他不用上報到那個
above officials
上面的官員
Master Ah Xiang
師傅阿翔
then the center does not
然後中央都不用
it's ok
這就OK了
Another kind of case is called secret channel serious case
另外一種案件叫做密道重案
The Case of the Dead Man's Robber
死人的強盜案件
This is the more important case
這就是比較重要的案件
after this case
這種案件發生之後
after your previous trial
你之前審完之後
You still send it all the way to the center
你還一路送到中央去
Especially the death penalty has to be sent to the Criminal Bureau
尤其是死刑要送到刑務局
this is punishment
這算是刑
So we're left with a lot of central archives now
所以我們現在留下來很多中央檔案
This file is called Criminal Division Basic
叫刑科基本這個檔案
Probably this kind of secret case
大概就是這種密道重案
Then collect the central archive from the place
然後從地方收藏中央檔案
such file
這樣的檔案
But if it is an ordinary small case
但是如果是一般的小案件
Including this kind of Jiedao case
包括這種介島案
In fact, it's all judged locally.
其實都在地方上判了就算
so what we're left with now
所以我們現在留下來的
Why do local cases
為什麼地方上的案件裡面
we can use it for research
我們可以拿來做研究
It is usually to study this
通常就是又來研究這種
mutual detection
所謂互分檢出
There are also relatively small cases of fishing
漁事案件還有這種比較小的
Everyday this small this
日常的這種小的這個
Baptism case
洗事案件
Then the big wash desk is out of our readjustment area
那大洗案頭就出了我們重調區
but interesting
但是很有意思
you go back to your first question today
你今天就回到你第一個問題
It's a question of cultural preservation
就是文性保存的問題
Will there be surplus points in its quantity?
那它的數量會不會有餘分
just because of the preservation of literacy
就因為文性的保存
will affect your ratio in terms of quantity
會影響你在數量上的比例
Of course it will and it's obvious
當然會 而且是很明顯的
and i say this
而且我這樣說
I dont know if this classmate can really pass an article
這位同學不曉得是不是真的能過一篇文章
A few years ago there was an article in American History Month Day Together
那前幾年有篇文章在美國歷史月曰一起
big dispute
很大一個爭執
That is, there are several scholars in mainland China
就是中國大陸有幾個學者
Research House is a scholar
研究房子是學者
an article he wrote in english
他用英文寫的篇文章
Statistical use of the lineage system
利用行科體本來統計
china in qing dynasty
中國在清朝
The change in the number of his violent keystrokes
他這個暴力按鍵數量的轉變
Change in the number of violent keystrokes
暴力按鍵數量轉變
Then he felt that after the conclusion
然後他覺得得到的結論之後
Many American scholars do not believe
很多美國學者就覺得不相信
why not believe
為什麼不相信
Because he counted the numbers from the Qing Dynasty
因為他這個數量統計從清朝結農
During the Xuantong period of the Qing Dynasty
遇到清朝這個宣統年間的時候
Attention everyone, when Xianfeng is in court
大家注意 賢峰朝的時候
And when the next few courts are here
還有後面幾個朝在的時候
central department
中央的行部
Or the central habit people have been blown
或者中央習慣的人已經被吹毀了
So its hard to talk about it. Lets talk about the period of the Taiping Heavenly Kingdom.
所以很難講說大家講講看太平天國時期
those places that happened in many war-torn areas
發生在很多戰亂地區的那些地方
Even if there is a secret case
即使發生了密道重案
These cases may be sent to the central referee
這些案件可能會送到中央裁判
Impossible, it was all war
不可能 原來都是戰亂
Where did you go before
你之前都不要跑到哪裡去了
So such statistics will be biased.
所以這樣的統計是會有偏差的
jigsaw puzzle
很多學者就拼圖
His statistics are problematic
他這樣的統計是有問題的
there is indeed a problem
的確真的有問題
so from this point of view
所以從這個角度
From this point of view, I also think
從這個角度我還覺得
The data in the table I just used is more reliable
我剛才用的那個表格的數據是比較可靠
Why?
為什麼?
Because there is no Taiping Heavenly Kingdom period near this place
因為從近這個地方沒有太平天國時期
not actually affected by his
沒有實際上受到他的
The actual impact of the war
實際上的戰亂的影響
So the stat I used
所以我用的那個統計數據
So this statistic
所以這個統計數據
Their number may be more representative than that of the Central Bank
他們這個數量可能還比中央行科基本的更具的代表性
more likely to reflect certain trends
更可以反映某些趨勢
Well, this is my future research.
好 這個是我未來要做的研究
not reached yet
現在還沒有達到
So in the future I will mention
所以未來我會再提
But the problem with this conclusion is very good
不過這個結論的問題非常好
good professor
教授好
Most of what the conclusion hearer hears is crime
結論者聽到的大部分都是犯罪
Most of what is heard is cut to
大部分都是聽到的都是切到
right
對
Then I'm more curious about
那我比較好奇的就是有關於
Of course after the crime it's about solving the case.
當然在犯罪之後要破案這件事
I see that kind of crime in the next year on being gay
我看到在明年就當中的同志連接那種犯罪
Of course he is down
他當然是往下
But it's cut at a glance
可是一看都是切到
But I'd rather know if it's a murder case
可是我比較想了解是命案
homicide
命案
That is to say, the murder part
也就是說這個命案部分
He has many possibilities for the past in ancient times
他有很多可能對於以前在古代的時候
historical time
歷史的時候
How did he solve the murder case?
他怎麼去做命案的破案
Also, does he have any tricks?
還有他有沒有哪一些的手法
yes can share with us
是可以跟我們分享一下
I think it must be interesting
我覺得一定很有趣
I rarely see that in books
那個我在書裡很少看到
And the second one is that I direct something
然後第二個就是我指導一些事
For example, like a few Tao Chaos before
比方說像幾個陶潮在之前
There will always be so-called Enemy Festival detectives
都會有所謂的敵人節這種神探
what we know
我們所知道的
We read what kind of detectives he had in the Ming and Qing Dynasties
我們讀到他在明清有什麼樣的神探
can point us a bit
是可以指得我們了一下
The more interesting part
比較有趣的這一段
Thank you, teacher
謝謝老師
ok thank you for the question
好 謝謝你這個問題
But this question was originally my biggest answer
但是這個問題本來是我最大的回答
real
真的
Because usually history if you don't read
因為通常歷史如果自己沒有看
If you study these things yourself
親自研究這些東西的話
we dare not say too much
我們都不敢說太多
because like secret case
因為像密案
You can see this statistic
大家可以看到這個統計裡面
The statistics of the part of the secret case in this quantity
密案的部分在這個數量上的統計
not too little
也不算少
For example, the secret case of Comrade Chaoyou Basic Middle
比如說同志朝有基本中間這個密案
put it in this
放在這個裡面
But this secret case is not
不過這個密案也不是
Everything we imagined was a secret case
我們想像中的全部都是密案
I don't want to be involved in this secret case
不願其中這個密案裡面
Also includes unmanned entities found
也包括了發現的無人實體
There are quite a few such proportions
這樣的佔比例也不少
So in fact, this still needs further research.
所以其實這個還需要進步的研究
usually
一般來講
Secret cases will of course have subsidies and autopsies
密案當然都會有補助、驗屍
these will have it
這些都會有它的
Details of these techniques and studies
這些手法和研究的細節
It is also worth doing research
也都很值得在做研究
But this part is not our specialty
但這個部分其實不是我們專業的
What we call for young researchers
我們所謂的為年輕的研究員
He actually studies this type of
他其實是研究這一類
So maybe his future
所以可能他未來的這個
He also belongs to one of the studies
他也就屬於一個那個研究
So future publication of his research would
所以未來的他的研究出版的話
should be able to see
應該可以看到
can have some answers
可以有些解答
In addition, the detective
另外說這個神探
actually
其實
should say this
應該說是這個
Taihan is like a god official
泰漢如神的官員吧
because of this
因為這樣子
It's hard for us to see the valley of the gods
我們很難看到說有什麼神谷
what about these things
就什麼這些東西
Some people just want to write lyrics after all
就有些人就畢竟想做寫詞
who knows
誰知道
Many officials are like this
很多官員是這樣
his magistrate
他的在他擔任這種地方官
then trial
然後審判
He feels very expressive
他自己覺得很有很表情
He thinks he is very Thai and like a god
他覺得他自己很泰漢如神
Usually he writes in his essay
通常他在自己的文競裡面
will leave these judgments
會留下這些署業判
He feels very proud of the sentences he passed.
他判了哪些判子他覺得很得意
He will leave his sentencing process behind
他會把他判判的過程留下來
This will appear in many people's articles
這在很多人的文章裡面會有
I dare not say who is a political judge
我不敢說有誰是政治審判
Or an official who judges a case like a trial
或者說是判案如審的官員
But many of these officials left behind
但是很多留下判如的這些官員
probably to show
大概都是為了彰顯
I'm pretty good at judging.
自己在判案這方面很了不起
verdict
判案如審
Indeed, if you look at these
的確你如果看這些判如的話
You'll find these officials adjudicating
你會發現這些官員在判案如審
There are really five sets
還真有這五套
He found another suspicious place
他發現有疑的地方還有一套
If we look at the actual case
如果我們從實際案件來看
From Guo Han to the actual case
從是國漢到實際案件
Niu Yize's case left a deep impression on us
牛一澤的案件讓我們印象很深刻
there is a personal reporter
就是有個人報官
He said how many pieces of clothes were stolen from my house
他說我家裡被偷了衣服多少件
Then privately vote how many pieces
然後私投多少件
still how so how
還是怎麼樣怎麼樣
Officials came to see the benefactor
官員來看看這位施主
just feel
就覺得
That is to say, you are definitely a fake
就是說你這個絕對是假造物
so as to get outside
從而得之外
Because the official looked directly at the Wu wearing
因為那個官員直接看這個武穿著
If you can collect such precious things at home today
你今天如果家裡可以收藏出那麼貴重的東西
Why Wushu is such a simple martial art
為什麼武穿著是那麼簡單的武術
So he can conclude except from the very beginning
所以他除了一開始就可以斷定
You are a slander
你這個是污告
it's none of those things
這根本就沒有這些事情
is pretending
是假裝
And by the way I also...
然後順便我還...
because here
因為講到這裡
I also say by the way
我還順便講一下
i see a lot of love child inside
我看到很多愛子裡面
many stolen maharajas
很多被偷的世主
if female
若是女性的話
are all women
都是往婦
And because the ex-wife is very rich
而且在於往婦都很有錢
so i keep joking about this
所以這個我一直開玩笑
When I saw this, I verified a statement from some historiography
我看到這裡就驗證了一些歷史學的一個說法
Talk about why many women in the folk want to be widows
說為什麼民間很多婦女要守寡
Because they said that this place is also Rational choice
因為他們又說這裡也是Rational choice
Yes, it's physical choice
對,是體性選擇
Why?
為什麼?
Because according to the Chinese law at that time
因為按照中國那個當時的法律
if you are used to it
還有習慣的話
if you speed up
你如果加速
After the husband passes away, if you dare to marry someone as a wife, your original husband's property will no longer be lost, and the marriage partner you originally brought will also be gone.
當夫過世之後,你做太太如果敢嫁妄,你原來夫家的財產不再沒有了,你原來帶過來的嫁妄也沒有了。
That's why many women prefer to be widowed. When I was widowed, my husband's family was still mine, and the marriages I brought were still mine, and I was still mine. The big deal is to leave it to me, this is if I dare to marry, I have nothing.
所以很多婦女寧願收寡,我收寡的時候,我家裡夫家還是我的,我帶來的這些嫁妄還是我的,我還是我的。大不了就留給我,這是我一敢嫁妄,我什麼都沒有了。
So many people say, why there are so many widows today, and there are so many widows who are really graduates and law-abiding widows, is related to this rational right.
所以很多人說,為什麼明天這個寡婦那麼多,真結業,真守法守寡的那麼多,跟這個理性權有關。
I said, at least from what I saw in this case, it is true that many of the stolen women were widows and married, and I did not marry in vain.
我說,至少從我看到這個案子裡面,真的很多被偷入婦女都是寡婦,被嫁了,我沒有嫁妄。
But when they sell newspapers, they talk about women, I am so pitiful, I have been a widow all my life, even if I have a little suspicion, I will be stolen into women, but you can see that she has a lot of marriages.
可是他們在報賣的時候,就跟關於婦女,我好可憐,我守寡一輩子,就算那麼一點點嫌妄就被偷入婦女,可是你可以看出來她的嫁妄不少。
Likewise, many people are widows.
同樣的,也很多人寡婦。
So the scholars behind it still have what they say
所以背后的读书人还有放贯所说
I am a reader of everything
我一切全读书人
all my life
我一切奴生
Wow how to live at home
哇 家里背后教的如何生活
But you find that the things behind the house are still valuable
可是你发现家里背后的东西还很值钱
a lot of money
很多钱
So Nusheng is writing Zhuangzi or everyone knows
所以奴生在写壮子或者大家知道
How much effort is spent when writing Zhuangzi
在写壮子的时候就是多少点花大力
Anyway, if the scene is not accepted
要反正现场不受理的话
that's not good
那就不好
So many people did not have the so-called shouchi at that time
所以很多人当时还有没有所谓受吃
So I was still writing Zhuangzi
所以当时还在写壮子
Not Zhou Xingzi's era
不是周星子年代
Designation of Zhou Xingzi's age
周星子年代的指定
This shouchi basic writing method is writing Zhuangzi
这个受吃基本的写方在写壮子
you really
你那个还真
I
我
can i ask this question
我可以问这个问题吗
our next last question
我们下一个最后一个问题
Let the gentleman at A3 ask first
要让那个A3的那个先生先问
Dear Teacher Gu
尊敬的顾老师
Ladies and gentlemen, everyone
各位姐妹大家寡言
Li Longzhang of the Qing Dynasty wanted to organize the subsequent Jinghui in Beiliang
清朝李隆章為了要籌組北梁隨之的經會
He does a sex act
他去做一個賣歡的動作
If we talk about the guilt at that time
如果說在當時的患罪的話
Is there a redemption situation
有沒有一個贖罪的情形
Is to use nutrition to redeem
就是用營養去贖罪
How much nutrition can be used to atone for a country change?
換國大概做就可以用多少營養去贖罪
Thanks
謝謝
thank you sir
謝謝這位先生
this question is important
這個問題很重要
But I can only say that I am not specialized in research
不過我只能說我不是專門研究
I have a postdoc
倒是我有一個博士後
The graduate of the University of Architecture is called KIM
建築大學的畢業叫KIM
he is doing this now
他現在正在做這樣
Generally speaking, let me explain a little bit
大致上我稍微說明一下
This crime in China is treason
中國的這個犯罪裡面是叛行
common crime
有一種叫做俗罪
That is to say, what sentence have you been sentenced to?
也就是說你被判了什麼刑
but you can spend money
但是你可以花錢
It's a vulgar crime that can be exonerated
可以免刑這種就是俗罪
Then at this time in the Ming Dynasty
那麼在明朝這時候
such sinful videos
這種俗罪的影片
Everyone can use vulgar crimes
大家想想的都可以用俗罪
may not be sentenced directly
可以不用直接判刑
It is also a serious crime
這也是比較重的罪
But the Qing Dynasty is different
可是清朝不一樣
Since the Qing Dynasty, many criminal laws
清朝開始很多那個刑法
is a veritable conviction
是切切實實的判罪
You are going to study this criminal law
你要去讀這個刑法
It's hard for you to sign it with money
你很難用錢去署它
So this is obviously in the Qing Dynasty
所以這個是很明顯在清朝的時候
Compared with the Ming Dynasty
這種情況跟明朝比較起來
it changes the actual
它就變更實際上
Then when it came to the middle and late Qing Dynasty
那麼當到了清朝中後期
Because the country's finances are poor
因為這個國家財政很差
So many so-called donations
所以很多所謂的捐納
Or there are a lot of cases of bureaucrats
或者是署官這個情況非常多
There are many cases of vulgar crimes
就俗罪的情況非常多
That's because the central government is short of money
那因為中央政府缺錢
He hopes to use the money to supplement
他希望用這些錢來補充
will become more and more complicated
會越來越複雜
will become more and more inconvenient
會越來越不便
But this atonement situation
但是這種贖罪的情況
if put in this steal
如果放在這個偷竊
rare
很少
Why?
為什麼?
because I just mentioned
因為我剛才也有提到
who actually stole
其實偷竊的人
most of the family
大部分家裡
Let's live these
下立活生這些
Restraint next time
下次克制
otherwise
要不然
Although there are occupations
雖然有職業
Although there is an identity
雖然有身份
But it's not necessarily a person who spends a lot of money
但是也不見得是很用錢的人
So usually this
所以通常這個
steal love this
偷竊的 愛這個
seldom atonement
很少是贖罪
Plus we just saw
再加上我們剛剛也看到
the stolen thing
偷竊的這個東西
If the price is not high
結價格不高的話
His luggage is heavy
他判的行李很重
probably a few
大概就是幾張
That's twenty. Thirty is amazing.
就是二十張 三十張了不起
so usually stolen love
所以通常偷竊的愛
Rarely sentenced
很少判署
rarely foreclosed
很少收贖
There is a way of redemption
有贖罪的方式解決
don't bother
也別得上一下
But the question you want to know
不過你那個想知道的問題
My future postdoctoral fellow
我未來我那個博士後
He will have some further
他會有一些更進一步的
this study
這個研究
very convenient
很方便
then maybe we can
那時候可能我們可以
find a better answer
找到一個更好的回答
Thanks
謝謝
You know that I have a little question I want to ask
你曉得說我一個小問題想請教
You said itchy head and dirty sixty
你說頭癢癢下臟六十
Am I dead?
我死翹翹嗎
dirty sixty that's not pretty
臟六十那是不漂亮的
In fact, according to his law
其實按照他這個法
Does he just pat lightly?
他就輕輕的拍嗎
When you are dirty and twenty or forty, you will lose your stomach
你當臟和二十四十就有點腸胃掉
So I thought it was weird then
所以我那時候就覺得很奇怪
this is their rule
這是他們這樣的規定
But in fact, most of the cases are actually one or two strokes
但是其實大部分的案子其實都在一兩下
So in fact, sometimes you can't take so many photos at all.
所以其實有時候根本照不到那麼多
And the report is in a trance
而且報告恍惚
In fact, many cases cannot be solved at all.
其實很多案子根本沒辦法解
Yes, that is, a small head
對 就是說一個小頭
even if he gets caught
即使他被抓到
It's hard for him to finally get to the closing part
他都很難最後到結案的部分
Sometimes it stays off for a long time
有時候就一直關一關了久
Then see me and die
然後再見到我就死了
Sometimes it may be possible to solve the case, probably with a small penalty
有時候可能可以解案,大概就是稍微處罰一下
Then hand it over to Baojia, and hand it over to the dentist
然後就交給保甲,交給牙醫去處理
control
就管束
Then when restraining him, if he commits another crime, he will be treated with questioning
然後管束的時候,如果他再犯的話就要用問所待
lock him up
把他關起來
But actually, let's just say
可是其實,話就說回來
I can't finish arresting criminals and concubines.
這個灌犯、灌妾其實抓不完
And the concubine actually knows the dentist himself
而且那個灌妾其實牙醫本身自己也知道
Many people know that Momoren is a concubine
很多人都知道,魔魔人就是灌妾
Then these concubines are a bit like our current professional climbers
那這些灌妾有一點像是我們現在的職業爬手
In fact, he climbed and climbed for a period of time
他其實爬一爬,就是到了一段時間
He closed the mountain again, and went back to his proper job
他又收山了,然後又去做正當職業
Then after a while of doing proper work, I went to climb, go to work, and go to screw
然後做正當職業過一會又去爬,又去忙,又去擰
So sometimes the real men catch those
所以有時候真正男抓的是那些
Obviously know that he is a concubine
明明知道他是灌妾
But just can't find evidence to catch him
但是就是找不到證據去抓他
This is like the Yi Zhimei bunny inside
這就是像那個易志梅小兔裡面
In fact, because I soon knew that Yi Zhimei, you are a little rabbit
其實因為我快都知道易志梅你就是小兔
But just can't find evidence to catch him
但是就是找不到證據去抓他
Because he stole probably all
因為他偷的東西大概都
So I won't sell or take it out
所以說不會賣或者不拿出來
so hard to catch
所以很難抓到
then this is all
那這個都是
I think it's all on paper
我覺得這個都是票面上
official articles
都是官樣的文章
what about the fact
那事實上呢
did you fight
到底有沒有打
right
對
Article Center of Peng Guo Articles
彭國文章的文章中央
In fact, we can't see it in the party
其實我們在黨內上看不到
Because in the end he ended up betting
因為最後他結狀化押之後
Or the official said
或者是這個官員就是說
Make up for this responsibility
補掉這個施責
But it didn't say that the responsibility of eating is the responsibility of the component
但是沒有說吃責到施責成分
It's usually about taking the blame
通常都是講說吃責
Including those supplements, if he
包括了那些補疫他如果
according to the law
按照法律
If he didn't catch it at the scene
都補疫他沒有在現場抓到的話
He also wants this account to be deducted
他也要這個帳筆也要抵折
But how to beat him again
但是到底怎麼把他再打多少
usually in writing
通常都是書面上寫寫的
we don't see what it actually means
我們沒有看到實際上的意思
so
所以
really
真的很
Thanks
謝謝
hard to decide
很難決定
because I can say anyway
因為我反正可以說要
It is recommended that everyone can raise a dog yellow dog
建議大家可以養狗黃狗
Compared with my dog, it is useless to say that this kind of dog is now a pet
比我家的狗,您一看到說這種狗現在的狗都是寵物沒有用
My family has a Shanzi dog. The puppy stole all the downstairs and only sent it outside.
我家養了養善子狗,小狗把樓下偷光光,還光送到出去
Because it's useless, now it's a pet, not a dog imitation, it's useless at all
因為沒有用,現在是寵物,不是養狗仿造,一點都沒有用
This is the end of our lecture today, thank you very much for this wonderful lecture by Professor Wu
我們今天的講演到此為止,非常感謝這個吳教授精彩的講演
Then the audience responded very enthusiastically, and everyone can invite him again in private
然後聽眾反應也非常熱烈,私下大家還可以跟他再請意
thank you all
謝謝大家